<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Energy-landscapes | rna-seq.at]]></title>
  <link href="http://rna-seq.at/blog/categories/energy-landscapes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rna-seq.at/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-09T18:41:39+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://rna-seq.at/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael T. Wolfinger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Memory-efficient RNA Energy Landscape Exploration]]></title>
    <link href="http://rna-seq.at/blog/2014/06/12/memory-efficient-RNA-energy-landscape-exploration/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-12T17:13:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://rna-seq.at/blog/2014/06/12/memory-efficient-RNA-energy-landscape-exploration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Discrete energy landscapes provide a valuable means for analyzing
non-equilibrium properties of biopolymers. RNA folding dynamics, for
example, can be described by a continuous-time Markov process at the level
of local minima, their corresponding basins of attraction and saddle points
connecting them.</p>

<p>A connected set of structures, often denoted <em>state space</em> is required for
energy landscape construction. While complete suboptimal folding of RNA is
practically impossible for chain lengths above 100nt, alternative
strategies to enumerate the lower part of the energy landscape emerged over
the last years.</p>

<p>We have recently extended previous work on global flooding by a local
flooding approach that minimizes memory consumption and published the
method in <em>Bioinformatics</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/30/18/2584"><strong>Memory-efficient RNA energy landscape
exploration</strong></a>  <br/>
<em>Martin Mann, Marcel Kucharík, Christoph Flamm, Michael T. Wolfinger</em> <br/>
Bioinformatics 2014 30(18):2584-2591 <br/>
<a href="http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btu337">DOI: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btu337</a></p>

<h2>Abstract</h2>

<blockquote><p>Motivation: Energy landscapes provide a valuable means for studying the
  folding dynamics of short RNA molecules in detail by modeling all
  possible structures and their transitions. Higher abstraction levels
  based on a macro-state decomposition of the landscape enable the study of
  larger systems; however, they are still restricted by huge memory
  requirements of exact approaches.</p>

<p>Results: We present a highly parallelizable local enumeration scheme that
  enables the computation of exact macro-state transition models with
  highly reduced memory requirements. The approach is evaluated on RNA
  secondary structure landscapes using a gradient basin definition for
  macro-states. Furthermore, we demonstrate the need for exact transition
  models by comparing two barrier-based approaches, and perform a detailed
  investigation of gradient basins in RNA energy landscapes.</p>

<p>Availability and implementation: Source code is part of the C++ Energy
  Landscape Library available at
  <a href="http://www.bioinf.uni-freiburg.de/Software/">http://www.bioinf.uni-freiburg.de/Software/</a>.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
