<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Publications | rna-seq.at]]></title>
  <link href="http://mtw.github.io/blog/categories/publications/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mtw.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-07T16:22:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mtw.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael T. Wolfinger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TSSAR: TSS Annotation Regime for dRNA-seq Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://mtw.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/tssar-tss-annotation-regime-for-drna-seq-data/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T22:22:41+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mtw.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/tssar-tss-annotation-regime-for-drna-seq-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In silico identification of bacterial transcription start sites (TSS) has
been a major challenge for the last years. To address this issue, we have
developped <a href="http://rna.tbi.univie.ac.at/TSSAR">TSSAR</a>, a statistical method
for analyzing dRNA-seq data, together with colleagues from the
Bioinformatics department at the University of Leipzig.</p>

<p>The TSSAR method paper is now out:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2105/15/89"><strong>TSSAR: TSS annotation regime for dRNA-seq
data</strong></a> <br/>
<em>Fabian Amman, Michael T Wolfinger, Ronny Lorenz, Ivo L Hofacker, Peter F
Stadler, Sven Findeiß</em><br/>
BMC Bioinformatics 2014, 15:89<br/>
<a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-15-89">DOI: 10.1186/1471-2105-15-89</a></p>

<h2>Abstract</h2>

<blockquote><p>Background</p>

<p>Differential RNA sequencing dRNA-seq is a high-throughput screening
technique designed to examine the architecture of bacterial operons in
general and the precise position of transcription start sites (TSS) in
particular. Hitherto, dRNA-seq data were analyzed by visualizing the
sequencing reads mapped to the reference genome and manually annotating
reliable positions. This is very labor intensive and, due to the
subjectivity, biased.</p>

<p>Results</p>

<p>Here, we present <strong>TSSAR</strong>, a tool for automated <em>de-novo</em> TSS annotation
from dRNA-seq data that respects the statistics of dRNA-seq
libraries. <strong>TSSAR</strong> uses the premise that the number of sequencing reads
starting at a certain genomic position within a transcriptional active
region follows a Poisson distribution with a parameter that depends on the
local strength of expression. The differences of two dRNA-seq library
counts thus follow a Skellam distribution. This provides a statistical
basis to identify significantly enriched primary transcripts.</p>

<p>We assessed the performance by analyzing a publicly available dRNA-seq
  data set using <strong>TSSAR</strong> and two simple approaches that utilize
  user-defined score cutoffs. We evaluated the power of reproducing the
  manual TSS annotation. Furthermore, the same data set was used to
  reproduce 74 experimentally validated TSS in <em>H. pylori</em> from reliable
  techniques such as RACE or primer extension. Both analyses showed that
  <strong>TSSAR</strong> outperforms the static cutoff-dependent approaches.</p>

<p>Conclusions</p>

<p>Having an automated and efficient tool for analyzing dRNA-seq data
  facilitates the use of the dRNA-seq technique and promotes its
  application to more sophisticated analysis. For instance, monitoring the
  plasticity and dynamics of the transcriptomal architecture triggered by
  different stimuli and growth conditions becomes possible.</p>

<p>The main asset of a novel tool for dRNA-seq analysis that reaches out to
a broad user community is usability. As such, we provide <strong>TSSAR</strong> both as
intuitive RESTful Web service [<a href="http://rna.tbi.univie.ac.at/TSSAR">http://rna.tbi.univie.ac.at/TSSAR</a>] together
with a set of post-processing and analysis tools, as well as a
stand-alone version for use in high-throughput dRNA-seq data analysis
pipelines.</p>

<p>Keywords</p>

<p>Differential RNA sequencing, dRNA-seq, TSS, Transcription start site
annotation, Transcriptome, RESTful Web service, Next generation sequencing</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
