<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Michael T. Wolfinger</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://michaelwolfinger.com/</id><updated>2025-07-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Exploring RNA Biology with Deep Learning Algorithms</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2025/blog/2025-07-18-Exploring-RNA-Biology-with-Deep-Learning/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-07-18T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2025-07-18:/blog/2025/blog/2025-07-18-Exploring-RNA-Biology-with-Deep-Learning/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The RNA biology journal is launching a new open‑access article collection called “Exploring RNA Biology with Deep Learning Algorithms” to bring together the latest breakthroughs at the intersection of transcriptomics, RNA structure prediction, molecular design and AI‑driven approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I will be serving as Guest Editor for the &lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://think.taylorandfrancis.com/article_collections/exploring-rna-biology-with-deep-learning-algorithms/"&gt;RNA Biology article collection “Exploring RNA Biology with Deep Learning Algorithms”&lt;/a&gt;. My aim is to curate articles that showcase how machine learning models can reveal hidden patterns in sequencing data, predict complex three dimensional RNA shapes with high accuracy and guide the design of novel RNA molecules for both research and therapeutic use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Exploring RNA Biology with Deep Learning Algorithms banner image" class="m-image" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/figures/RNABiolDL2025_banner.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;section id="why-this-collection-matters"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why This Collection Matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RNA plays a central role in virtually every biological process, from gene regulation to the assembly of protein complexes. Yet its complexity poses formidable analytical challenges. Over the past few years, deep learning has transformed the way we decode protein structures and genomic data. Now, we stand on the edge of a similar revolution in RNA biology:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncover hidden patterns&lt;/strong&gt; in high‑throughput sequencing data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predict RNA modifications&lt;/strong&gt; and their functional impacts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model secondary &amp;amp; tertiary structures&lt;/strong&gt; with unprecedented accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design synthetic RNAs&lt;/strong&gt; for therapeutics and synthetic biology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map RNA–protein interactions&lt;/strong&gt; and regulatory switches at scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="what-were-looking-for"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What We’re Looking For&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By pooling insights from biochemists, computational biologists and AI specialists, this special issue aims to chart the next frontier in RNA research. We welcome original research, methods papers and in‑depth reviews on topics including (but not limited to):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;📈 Deep learning for transcriptome analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🔍 AI models of RNA modifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🏗️ Secondary &amp;amp; tertiary structure prediction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;✨ AI‑driven RNA design &amp;amp; editing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🧩 RNA–protein interaction mapping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🔄 Automated annotation of RNA architectures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="advisory-panel"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Advisory Panel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to be joined by two leading experts in RNA science as Guest Advisors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://www.jic.ac.uk/people/yilliang-ding/"&gt;Prof. Yiliang Ding&lt;/a&gt; (John Innes Centre): Pioneer of in vivo RNA structure mapping and chemical probing methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://life.tsinghua.edu.cn/lifeen/info/1034/1075.htm"&gt;Prof. Qiangfeng Cliff Zhang&lt;/a&gt; (Tsinghua University): Specialist in AI‑informed big‑data analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="details-submission"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Details &amp;amp; Submission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-row"&gt;
&lt;div class="m-col-l-4 m-col-m-4 m-container-inflatable"&gt;
&lt;aside class="m-block m-info"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Manuscript Deadline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;30 November 2025&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="m-col-l-4 m-col-m-4 m-container-inflatable"&gt;
&lt;aside class="m-block m-info"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Submission&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://think.taylorandfrancis.com/article_collections/exploring-rna-biology-with-deep-learning-algorithms"&gt;Submit Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="m-col-l-4 m-col-m-4 m-container-inflatable"&gt;
&lt;aside class="m-block m-info"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Journal Contact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href="mailto:chao.xiao@tayloranfrancis.com"&gt;Ms. Chao Xiao&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="join-the-conversation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Join the Conversation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have questions about a potential submission, or want to discuss a cutting‑edge idea? Feel free to reach out via the &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/contact/"&gt;contact form&lt;/a&gt; on this site or &lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/michaelwolfinger/"&gt;connect with me on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="outreach"></category><category term="AI"></category><category term="synthetic biology"></category></entry><entry><title>Insect-specific flaviviruses evade antiviral RNAi</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2024/blog/2024-10-15-Pan-flavivirus-analysis-reveals-sfRNA-independent-3-UTR-biased-siRNA-production-from-an-insect-specific-flavivirus/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-10-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2024-10-15:/blog/2024/blog/2024-10-15-Pan-flavivirus-analysis-reveals-sfRNA-independent-3-UTR-biased-siRNA-production-from-an-insect-specific-flavivirus/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we explore the role of RNA interference (RNAi) in mosquito immunity by comparing viral small interfering RNA (siRNA) profiles across different  insect-specific flaviviruses&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="3UTR of KRV, CFAV, and CxFV" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Besson-2024.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RNAi is a key antiviral defense in mosquitoes, where viral double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) is processed into viral small interfering RNAs (vsiRNAs), which then target viral RNA for degradation. We found that for most flaviviruses, vsiRNAs were evenly distributed across the viral genome. However, for clasic insect-specific flaviviruses (cISFs), especially the Kamiti River virus (KRV), vsiRNA production was highly biased toward the 3' untranslated region (UTR) of the viral genome. This was particularly striking for KRV, which has a uniquely long 3' UTR of about 1.2 kilobases. Over 95% of KRV-derived vsiRNAs were mapped to this region, suggesting a distinct RNA processing mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the study explores the role of subgenomic flavivirus RNAs (sfRNAs) in vsiRNA production. sfRNAs are produced when the XRN1 exoribonuclease stalls on structured RNA elements in the 3' UTR of flavivirus genomes, and they play various roles in viral replication and immune evasion. For KRV, two major sfRNAs were identified (sfRNA1 and sfRNA2), corresponding to predicted XRN1-resistant elements in the 3' UTR. However, despite the high abundance of these sfRNAs, the 3' UTR-biased vsiRNA production in KRV was found to be independent of sfRNA formation. This indicates that KRV's siRNA profile is shaped by other factors, likely a distinct viral RNA species processed by the RNAi machinery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings suggest that KRV and other cISFs have evolved unique mechanisms to evade the mosquito's antiviral RNAi response, potentially using the highly structured 3' UTR as a decoy. This discovery provides new insights into how insect-specific flaviviruses interact with mosquito immune systems and could have implications for understanding the evolution of arboviruses and their transmission dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RNA interference (RNAi) plays an essential role in mosquito antiviral immunity, but it is not known whether viral small interfering RNA (siRNA) profiles differ between mosquito-borne and mosquito-specific viruses. A pan-Orthoflavivirus analysisin Aedes albopictus cells revealed that viral siRNAs were evenly distributed across the viral genome of most representatives of the Flavivirus genus. In contrast, siRNA production was biased toward the 3' untranslated region (UTR) of the genomes of classical insect-specific flaviviruses (cISF), which was most pronounced for Kamiti River virus (KRV), a virus with a unique, 1.2 kb long 3' UTR. KRV-derived siRNAs were produced in high quantities and almost exclusively mapped to the 3' UTR. We mapped the 5' end of KRV subgenomic flavivirus RNAs (sfRNAs), products of the 5'−3' exoribonuclease XRN1/Pacman stalling on secondary RNA structures in the 3' UTR of the viral genome. We found that KRV produces high copy numbers of a long, 1,017 nt sfRNA1 and a short, 421 nt sfRNA2, corresponding to two predicted XRN1-resistant elements. Expression of both sfRNA1 and sfRNA2 was reduced in Pacman-deficient Aedes albopictus cells; however, this did not correlate with a shift in viral siRNA profiles. We suggest that cISFs, particularly KRV, developed a unique mechanism to produce high amounts of siRNAs as a decoy for the antiviral RNAi response in an sfRNA-independent manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2024/blog/2024-10-15-Pan-flavivirus-analysis-reveals-sfRNA-independent-3-UTR-biased-siRNA-production-from-an-insect-specific-flavivirus/"&gt;Pan-flavivirus analysis reveals sfRNA-independent, 3’UTR-biased siRNA production from an Insect-Specific Flavivirus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Benoit Besson, Gijs J. Overheul, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Sandra Junglen, Ronald P. van Rij&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;J. Virol.&lt;/em&gt; e01215-24 (2024) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.01215-24"&gt;doi:10.1128/jvi.01215-24&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Besson-2024__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="xrRNA"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Xinyang flavivirus is a novel tick-borne Orthoflavivirus</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2024/blog/2024-05-29-Xingyang-flavivirus-from-Haemaphysalis-flava-ticks-defines-a-basal-likely-tick-only-Orthoflavivirus-clade/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2024-05-29:/blog/2024/blog/2024-05-29-Xingyang-flavivirus-from-Haemaphysalis-flava-ticks-defines-a-basal-likely-tick-only-Orthoflavivirus-clade/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we report the discovery of Xinyang flavivirus (XiFV), a novel virus isolated from Haemaphysalis flava ticks in China. Through phylogenetic analysis, we found that XiFV is closely related to other tick-only flaviviruses, such as Mpulungu flavivirus (MPFV) from Zambia and Ngoye virus (NGOV) from Senegal. This positions XiFV in a unique clade of orthoflaviviruses, a group that seems to infect only ticks, without any known vertebrate host&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Figure 2 from Wang et al. (2024) doi:10.1099/jgv.0.001991" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Wang-2024.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What sets XiFV apart from many other flaviviruses is its apparent restriction to an arthropod-only life cycle. While most flaviviruses are transmitted between ticks and mammals or birds, XiFV shows no evidence of such transmission. Its genome exhibits traits similar to insect-specific flaviviruses, reinforcing the idea that it might be confined to ticks. Notably, XiFV and its close relatives lack a crucial protein cleavage site found in flaviviruses that infect vertebrates, further suggesting their life cycle is restricted to tick populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a structural level, XiFV shares several characteristics with other orthoflaviviruses, particularly in the formation of complex RNA structures in its 3′ untranslated region. These structures are known to play a role in viral replication and evasion of host immune defenses. Our findings add to the growing understanding that a distinct group of tick-borne flaviviruses might not need a vertebrate host to survive, opening the door to further research into their ecology and interactions with other pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this new virus continues to be studied, it highlights the importance of understanding the diverse life cycles and evolutionary pressures shaping tick-borne viruses, which could have broader implications for public health and virology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wang-2024.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wang-2024.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick-borne orthoflaviviruses (TBFs) are classified into three conventional groups based on genetics and ecology: mammalian, seabird and probable-TBF group. Recently, a fourth basal group has been identified in Rhipicephalus ticks from Africa: Mpulungu flavivirus (MPFV) in Zambia and Ngoye virus (NGOV) in Senegal. Despite attempts, isolating these viruses in vertebrate and invertebrate cell lines or intracerebral injection of newborn mice with virus-containing homogenates has remained unsuccessful. In this study, we report the discovery of Xinyang flavivirus (XiFV) in Haemaphysalis flava ticks from Xìnyáng, Henan Province, China. Phylogenetic analysis shows that XiFV was most closely related to MPFV and NGOV, marking the first identification of this tick orthoflavivirus group in Asia. We developed a reverse transcriptase quantitative PCR assay to screen wild-collected ticks and egg clutches, with absolute infection rates of 20.75% in adult females and 15.19% in egg clutches, suggesting that XiFV could be potentially spread through transovarial transmission. To examine potential host range, dinucleotide composition analyses revealed that XiFV, MPFV and NGOV share a closer composition to classical insect-specific orthoflaviviruses than to vertebrate-infecting TBFs, suggesting that XiFV could be a tick-only orthoflavivirus. Additionally, both XiFV and MPFV lack a furin cleavage site in the prM protein, unlike other TBFs, suggesting these viruses might exist towards a biased immature particle state. To examine this, chimeric Binjari virus with XIFV- prME (bXiFV) was generated, purified and analysed by SDS-PAGE and negative-stain transmission electron microscopy, suggesting prototypical orthoflavivirus size (~50 nm) and bias towards uncleaved prM. In silico structural analyses of the 3'-untranslated regions show that XiFV forms up to five pseudo-knot-containing stem-loops and a prototypical orthoflavivirus dumbbell element, suggesting the potential for multiple exoribonuclease-resistant RNA structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1099/jgv.0.001991"&gt;Xinyang flavivirus, from Haemaphysalis flava ticks in Henan province, China, defines a basal, likely tick-only flavivirus clade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lan-Lan Wang, Qia Cheng, Natalee D. Newton, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Mahali S. Morgan, Andrii Slonchak, Alexander A. Khromykh, Tian-Yin Cheng, Rhys H. Parry&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;J. Gen. Virol.&lt;/em&gt; 105(5) (2024) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1099/jgv.0.001991"&gt;doi:10.1099/jgv.0.001991&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wang-2024.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Mpulungu_Virus_is_a_novel_tick_flavivirus_from_Africa/"&gt;An African Tick Flavivirus Forming an Independent Clade Exhibits Unique Exoribonuclease-Resistant RNA Structures in the Genomic 3’-Untranslated Region&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hayato Harima, Yasuko Orba, Shiho Torii, Yongjin Qiu, Masahiro Kajihara, Yoshiki Eto, Naoya Matsuta, Bernard M. Hang’ombe, Yuki Eshita, Kentaro Uemura, Keita Matsuno, Michihito Sasaki, Kentaro Yoshii, Ryo Nakao, William W. Hall, Ayato Takada, Takashi Abe, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Martin Simuunza, Hirofumi Sawa&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sci. Rep.&lt;/em&gt; 11:4883 (2021) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-84365-9"&gt;doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-84365-9&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Harima-2021.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="molecular epidemiology"></category><category term="One Health"></category><category term="xrRNA"></category><category term="novel viruses"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Beyond Pango: The future of virus lineage classification</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2024/blog/2024-02-12-A-framework-for-automated-scalable-designation-of-viral-pathogen-lineages-from-genomic-data/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-02-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2024-02-12:/blog/2024/blog/2024-02-12-A-framework-for-automated-scalable-designation-of-viral-pathogen-lineages-from-genomic-data/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Keeping pace with ever-changing viruses is a challenge. This study unveils an automated system for classifying viral lineages based on genetics, offering a faster and more objective approach&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Automated lineage designation of Venezuelan Equine Encephalitis complex viruses" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__McBroome-2024.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tracking and categorizing viruses like SARS-CoV-2 effectively is crucial for scientific research and public health initiatives. Traditionally, scientists used naming conventions based on geographical locations or specific characteristics to identify variants. However, given the rapid mutations in viruses, even a single mutation can create a new lineage, complicating classification. Additionally, the vast amount of genomic data associated with viruses like SARS-CoV-2 presents challenges for existing classification methods, which often involve manual curation and crowd-sourced proposals, leading to time-consuming processes and potential biases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To overcome these challenges, we introduce Autolin, an automated system that utilizes genetic data to classify viral lineages. This approach proves to be efficient even with extensive datasets, offering a much quicker and more objective method compared to manual curation. The prospect of analyzing and classifying rapidly evolving viruses in real-time represents a significant advancement in our ability to monitor and comprehend these pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autolin provides several benefits over current methods. Its speed allows researchers to keep up with the fast-paced evolution of viruses, while its reliance on genetic data helps eliminate biases inherent in manual curation or crowd-sourced approaches. This objectivity is crucial for ensuring clear and consistent communication regarding viral threats. Moreover, Autolin is highly scalable and can be applied to any virus, not just SARS-CoV-2, making it invaluable for addressing future public health challenges. Additionally, Autolin offers flexibility by allowing users to integrate information about the significance of specific mutations, leading to classifications that are more relevant from an epidemiological perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Autolin is not without limitations and requires continuous updates as new data emerges, it represents a significant advancement in our ability to monitor and understand viruses. As genomic sequencing becomes more widespread globally, automated tools like Autolin will be indispensable for effectively managing future public health crises. With faster, more impartial, and scalable virus classification, researchers and public health officials will be better equipped to confront emerging pathogens and protect public health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/McBroome-2024.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/McBroome-2024.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pathogen lineage nomenclature systems are a key component of effective communication and collaboration for researchers and public health workers. Since February 2021, the Pango dynamic lineage nomenclature for SARS-CoV-2 has been sustained by crowdsourced lineage proposals as new isolates were sequenced. This approach is vulnerable to time-critical delays as well as regional and personal bias. Here we developed a simple heuristic approach for dividing phylogenetic trees into lineages, including the prioritization of key mutations or genes. Our implementation is efficient on extremely large phylogenetic trees consisting of millions of sequences and produces similar results to existing manually curated lineage designations when applied to SARS-CoV-2 and other viruses including chikungunya virus, Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus complex and Zika virus. This method offers a simple, automated and consistent approach to pathogen nomenclature that can assist researchers in developing and maintaining phylogeny-based classifications in the face of ever-increasing genomic datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/doi:10.1038/s41564-023-01587-5"&gt;A framework for automated scalable designation of viral pathogen lineages from genomic data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Jakob McBroome, Adriano de Bernardi Schneider, Cornelius Roemer, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Angie S. Hinrichs, Aine N. O’Toole, Chris Ruis, Yatish Turakhia, Andrew Rambaut, and Russell Corbett-Detig&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Nature Microbiol.&lt;/em&gt;  9:550–560 (2024) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/doi:10.1038/s41564-023-01587-5"&gt;doi:10.1038/s41564-023-01587-5&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/McBroome-2024.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="new method"></category><category term="tools"></category><category term="molecular epidemiology"></category><category term="One Health"></category></entry><entry><title>The pivotal role of virus bioinformatics in global health</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2023/Virus-Bioinformatics-Paving-the-Way-for-One-Health/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-11-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2023-11-03:/blog/2023/Virus-Bioinformatics-Paving-the-Way-for-One-Health/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On One Health Day, we recognize the intricate links between human, animal, and environmental health, underscored by the emergence of novel viruses like SARS-CoV-2. This post, crafted for a lay audience, delves into the critical contributions of virus bioinformatics in understanding and combating infectious diseases. It emphasizes the importance of predicting RNA structures for understanding RNA viruses and discusses the role of genomic epidemiology in tracking viral spread and evolution&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Health Day&lt;/strong&gt;, celebrated on November 3rd each year, highlights the interconnectedness of human, animal, and environmental health. Viruses, as microscopic pathogens capable of infecting all three realms, serve as a stark reminder of this interconnectedness. The emergence of novel viruses, such as SARS-CoV-2, the virus responsible for COVID-19, has underscored the need for a &lt;em&gt;One Health approach&lt;/em&gt; to combat infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virus bioinformatics, a field that utilizes computational methods to analyze viral genomes and proteins, plays a pivotal role in this &lt;em&gt;One Health&lt;/em&gt; approach. By decoding the genetic blueprints of viruses, bioinformaticians can identify patterns, predict mutations, and understand how viruses interact with their hosts. This information is invaluable for developing effective diagnostics, vaccines, and treatments for viral diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="the-importance-of-rna-structure-prediction-for-understanding-rna-viruses"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Importance of RNA Structure Prediction for Understanding RNA Viruses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many viruses, including HIV, influenza, and hepatitis C, use RNA as their genetic material. Unlike DNA, which has a double-stranded structure, RNA is single-stranded and can fold into complex shapes. These RNA structures are essential for viral replication and function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RNA structure prediction is a challenging task due to the flexibility and complexity of RNA molecules. However, advances in computational methods have made it possible to predict the structures of many viral RNAs. This information has provided valuable insights into how these viruses replicate, interact with host cells, and evade the immune system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="studying-the-genomic-epidemiology-of-viruses"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Studying the Genomic Epidemiology of Viruses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genomic epidemiology is the study of how viral genomes change over time and space. This information can be used to track the spread of viruses, identify the origins of outbreaks, and understand how viruses evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bioinformatic tools are essential for genomic epidemiology studies. They allow researchers to analyze large datasets of viral sequences, identify mutations, and reconstruct the evolutionary history of viruses. This information is crucial for informing public health interventions and developing effective control strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="other-applications-of-virus-bioinformatics"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other Applications of Virus Bioinformatics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the applications discussed above, virus bioinformatics is also used to study a wide range of other viral phenomena, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Viral pathogenesis: Understanding how viruses cause disease&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Viral host interactions: Identifying cellular factors that are important for viral replication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Antiviral resistance: Studying how viruses evolve to escape the effects of antiviral drugs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-future-of-virus-bioinformatics"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Future of Virus Bioinformatics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virus bioinformatics is a rapidly evolving field, and new computational methods are being developed all the time. These methods will allow us to gain even deeper insights into the biology of viruses and to develop more effective strategies to combat them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continue to face the challenges of emerging infectious diseases, virus bioinformatics will remain an indispensable tool for protecting human, animal, and environmental health. By fostering collaboration between bioinformaticians, virologists, public health experts, and other stakeholders, we can harness the power of virus bioinformatics to create a healthier world for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="outreach"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="One Health"></category></entry><entry><title>Zika virus: Unlocking cures with G-quadruplex structures</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2023/blog/2023-10-23-The-3-prime-terminal-region-of-Zika-virus-RNA-contains-a-conserved-G-quadruplex-and-is-unfolded-by-human-DDX17/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2023-10-23:/blog/2023/blog/2023-10-23-The-3-prime-terminal-region-of-Zika-virus-RNA-contains-a-conserved-G-quadruplex-and-is-unfolded-by-human-DDX17/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We identified a conserved G-quadruplex structure in the Zika virus's 3' terminal region, which interacts with human DEAD-box helicases, DDX3X and DDX17. These findings suggest new potential therapeutic targets for the development of treatments against the virus&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="G-Quadruplex in the terminal region of the Zika virus genome" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Gemmill-2024.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zika virus (ZIKV) is a global health threat. With nearly 100 countries designated as ZIKV risk areas and a substantial impact on fetal development, innovative approaches to combat the virus are crucial. In our recent paper, we delved into the intricate world of ZIKV RNA structures and human protein interactions, sheding light on a potential therapeutic application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G-quadruplexes (G4s) are particularly interesting RNA structures that play various roles in viruses and all domains of life. These structures can regulate transcription, translation, and even maintain genome stability. In ZIKV, a potential G-quadruplex sequence was located in the 3' terminal region (TR) using a quadruplex-forming G-rich sequences Mapper, but its conservation and role in larger ZIKV RNA transcripts remained unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research establishes that the ZIKV 3' TR G4 is conserved across all ZIKV isolates and retains its structure in a 3' TR full-length transcript. This G4 formation was confirmed using pyridostatin and the BG4 G4-recognizing antibody binding assays. Crucially, we found that human DEAD-box helicases, DDX3X132-607 and DDX17135-555, bind to the 3' TR, and that DDX17135-555 unfolds the G4 in the 3' TR. This unraveling of the G4 structure presents an opportunity for therapeutic targeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the ZIKV G4 structure and its interactions with human proteins is essential for a comprehensive One Health approach, which recognizes the interconnectedness of human, animal, and environmental health. ZIKV, transmitted primarily by Aedes mosquitoes, not only leads to congenital disabilities in utero but can also cause debilitating symptoms in adults. A nuanced understanding of the virus's replication mechanisms through our study can facilitate the development of targeted treatments, reducing the disease burden on vulnerable populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our discovery allows us to contemplate potential treatments using G4 binding molecules or other molecules that disrupt human DDX17–3' SL interaction. Though more research is needed to understand the function of the 3' SL G4 during viral replication, our study lays the groundwork for innovative therapeutics against ZIKV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the absence of ZIKV treatments or vaccines, our research sheds light on the potential of targeting specific RNA structures and their interactions with human proteins. By understanding and leveraging these interactions, we may open new doors in the fight against ZIKV, contributing to a holistic One Health strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for more insights into the world of RNA structures and their roles in viral replication, as we continue our quest to unveil novel therapeutic possibilities against Zika virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Gemmill-2024.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Gemmill-2024.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zika virus (ZIKV) infection remains a worldwide concern, and currently no effective treatments or vaccines are available. Novel therapeutics are an avenue of interest that could probe viral RNA-human protein communication to stop viral replication. One specific RNA structure, G-quadruplexes (G4s), possess various roles in viruses and all domains of life, including transcription and translation regulation and genome stability, and serves as nucleation points for RNA liquid-liquid phase separation. Previous G4 studies on ZIKV using a quadruplex forming G-rich sequences Mapper located a potential G-quadruplex sequence in the 3′ terminal region (TR) and was validated structurally using a 25-mer oligo. It is currently unknown if this structure is conserved and maintained in a large ZIKV RNA transcript and its specific roles in viral replication. Using bioinformatic analysis and biochemical assays, we demonstrate that the ZIKV 3′ TR G4 is conserved across all ZIKV isolates and maintains its structure in a 3′ TR full-length transcript. We further established the G4 formation using pyridostatin and the BG4 G4-recognizing antibody binding assays. Our study also demonstrates that the human DEAD-box helicases, DDX3X132-607 and DDX17135-555, bind to the 3′ TR and that DDX17135-555 unfolds the G4 present in the 3′ TR. These findings provide a path forward in potential therapeutic targeting of DDX3X or DDX17’s binding to the 3′ TR G4 region for novel treatments against ZIKV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2023/blog/2023-10-23-The-3-prime-terminal-region-of-Zika-virus-RNA-contains-a-conserved-G-quadruplex-and-is-unfolded-by-human-DDX17/"&gt;The 3’ terminal region of Zika virus RNA contains a conserved G-quadruplex and is unfolded by human DDX17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Danielle L. Gemmill, Corey R. Nelson, Maulik D. Badmalia, Higor S. Pereira, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, and Trushar Patel&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Biochem. Cell Biol.&lt;/em&gt; 102(1):96–105 (2024) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1139/bcb-2023-0036"&gt;doi:10.1139/bcb-2023-0036&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Gemmill-2024.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="RNA-Protein interaction"></category><category term="non-coding RNA"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>RNA-protein complex refinement using AI modeling and docking</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2023/blog/2023-06-09-A-Structural-Refinement-Technique-for-Protein-RNA-Complexes-Using-Combination-of-AI-based-Modeling-and-Flexible-Docking-A-Study-of-Musashi-1-Protein/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2023-06-09:/blog/2023/blog/2023-06-09-A-Structural-Refinement-Technique-for-Protein-RNA-Complexes-Using-Combination-of-AI-based-Modeling-and-Flexible-Docking-A-Study-of-Musashi-1-Protein/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This study presents an efficient technique for refining protein-RNA complexes using artifilial intelligence (AI) based modeling and flexible docking. The method, utilizing parallel cascade selection molecular dynamics (PaCS-MD), accelerates conformational sampling of flexible RNA regions and produces high-quality complex models. Experimental validation demonstrates its superiority over template-based modeling, suggesting its potential for constructing complexes with non-canonical RNA-protein interactions&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Association complex of Musashi RBD1 and RBD with a target RNA" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Darai-2023.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the interactions between proteins and RNA is essential for unraveling the mysteries of cellular functions. In a recent study, we proposed an innovative and efficient technique to accurately model the interactions between proteins and RNA, leading to insights that have the potential to advance the fields of structural biology and drug design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a protein interacts with RNA, it forms what is known as a protein-RNA complex. Constructing accurate models of these complexes is a formidable challenge. Traditional methods, such as template-based modeling, involve creating the overall conformation and then manually connecting RNA with a protein’s RNA-binding domains (RBDs). However, this doesn't always lead to biologically plausible complexes, highlighting the urgent need for improved methodologies to simulate protein-RNA association complexes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we were particularly interested in the RNA-binding protein Musashi-1 (MSI1) and its interaction with RNA through RNA-binding domains (MSI1-RBDs), we proposed a two-step approach: first, we utilized the AI-based modeling technique Alphafold2 to predict a 3D structure of the MSI1-RBDs based on the amino-acid sequences in humans. Following this, we used a flexible docking technique called PaCS-MD to construct the protein-RNA complexes. Unlike traditional methods that manually ligate RNA to the protein, PaCS-MD automatically constructs the complexes, providing a more natural interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure the validity of the constructed complexes, we evaluated their structural stability using the SIE (Solvation Interaction Energy) method. The results confirmed previous studies, showing that a core set of three nucleotides in MSI1-RBDs plays a significant role in the interaction with the target RNA. Moreover, we identified crucial residues for RNA-binding that aligned well with previous findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our method offers a significant advantage over conventional techniques. Unlike traditional homology modeling methods, such as Phyre2, our technique captures the essential transitions required for forming protein-RNA complexes. However, we acknowledge that the technique relies on having initial structural information from NMR (Nuclear Magnetic Resonance) coordinates. Without this data, achieving accurate flexible docking can be challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study provides a compelling demonstration of constructing plausible protein-RNA complexes using a combination of AI-based modeling and flexible docking. This research takes us one step closer to deciphering the complex interactions between proteins and RNA, paving the way for advancements in personalized medicine and drug discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Darai-2023.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Darai-2023.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An efficient structural refinement technique for protein-RNA complexes is proposed based on a combination of AI-based modeling and flexible docking. Specifically, an enhanced sampling method called parallel cascade selection molecular dynamics (PaCS-MD) was extended to include flexible docking to construct protein-RNA complexes from those obtained by AI-based modeling (AlphaFold2). With the present technique, the conformational sampling of flexible RNA regions is accelerated by PaCS-MD, enabling one to construct plausible models for protein-RNA complexes. For demonstration, PaCS-MD constructed several protein-RNA complexes of the RNA-binding Musashi-1 (MSI1) family of proteins, which were validated by comparing a group of crucial residues for RNA-binding with experimental complexes. Our analyses suggest that PaCS-MD improves the quality of complex modeling compared to the standard protocol based on template-based modeling (Phyre2). Furthermore, PaCS-MD could also be a beneficial technique for constructing complexes of non-native RNA-binding to proteins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1246/bcsj.20230092"&gt;A Structural Refinement Technique for Protein-RNA Complexes Using a Combination of AI-based Modeling and Flexible Docking: A Study of Musashi-1 Protein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nitchakan Darai, Kowit Hengphasatporn, Peter Wolschann, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Yasuteru Shigeta, Thanyada Rungrotmongkol, Ryuhei Harada&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;B. Chem. Soc. Jpn.&lt;/em&gt; (2023)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2022/Theoretical-studies-on-RNA-recognition-by-Musashi1-RNA-binding-protein/"&gt;Theoretical studies on RNA recognition by Musashi 1 RNA–binding protein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nitchakan Darai, Panupong Mahalapbutr, Peter Wolschann, Vannajan Sanghiran Lee, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolﬁnger&lt;/span&gt;, Thanyada Rungrotmongkol&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sci. Rep.&lt;/em&gt; 12:12137 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-16252-w"&gt;doi:10.1038/s41598-022-16252-w&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Darai-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2019/Musashi-Binding-Elements-in-Zika-and-Related-Flavivirus-3UTRs-A-Comparative-Study-in-Silico/"&gt;Musashi Binding Elements in Zika and Related Flavivirus 3’UTRs: A Comparative Study in Silico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Adriano de Bernardi Schneider, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sci. Rep.&lt;/em&gt; 9(1):6911 (2019) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-43390-5"&gt;doi:10.1038/s41598-019-43390-5&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/deBernardiSchneider-2019a.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="new method"></category><category term="3D"></category><category term="RNA-Protein interaction"></category><category term="AI"></category></entry><entry><title>RNA–RNA interaction analysis of Japanese encephalitis virus</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2023/Investigating-RNA-RNA-interactions-through-computational-and-biophysical-analysis/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-03-31T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2023-03-31:/blog/2023/Investigating-RNA-RNA-interactions-through-computational-and-biophysical-analysis/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Unraveling the intricate RNA-RNA interactions in Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV) opens new possibilities for understanding viral replication and designing antiviral therapeutics, as our recent study reveals the importance of a conserved cyclization sequence in driving these interactions&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Graphical abstract of doi:10.1093/nar/gkad223" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Mrozowich-2023.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study, we have utilized a unique combination of computational and biophysical techniques to investigate RNA-RNA interactions in Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV). We identified a specific JEV isolate with a hypothesized high-affinity interaction, and then employed various biophysical characterization methods to validate and characterize this interaction. Through size-exclusion chromatography coupled with multi-angle light scattering (SEC-MALS) and analytical ultracentrifugation (AUC), we demonstrated the direct interaction between the 5' and 3' terminal regions (TRs) of JEV with nanomolar affinity and 1:1 stoichiometry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our computational analysis supported a kinetic favorability of the cyclization sequence interaction and its competitive advantage over potential homo-dimer RNA interactions. This provides valuable insights into the replication pathway/mechanism of flavivirus NS5 in replicating the viral genome. Our study also presents a low-resolution ab initio model that offers a potential architectural arrangement of this RNA-RNA interaction in solution. These findings lay a solid foundation for the development of pharmaceutical therapies targeting viral replication through interruption of the cyclization sequence, and also shed light on the fundamental understanding of RNA-RNA interactions in flaviviruses and other viral systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study's insights into RNA-RNA interactions in Japanese encephalitis virus align with the One Health approach, highlighting the potential for antiviral therapies to benefit both human and animal health while considering the broader ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mrozowich-2023.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mrozowich-2023.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous viruses utilize essential long-range RNA–RNA genome interactions, specifically flaviviruses. Using Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV) as a model system, we computationally predicted and then biophysically validated and characterized its long-range RNA–RNA genomic interaction. Using multiple RNA computation assessment programs, we determine the primary RNA–RNA interacting site among JEV isolates and numerous related viruses. Following in vitro transcription of RNA, we provide, for the first time, characterization of an RNA–RNA interaction using size-exclusion chromatography coupled with multi-angle light scattering and analytical ultracentrifugation. Next, we demonstrate that the 5′ and 3′ terminal regions of JEV interact with nM affinity using microscale thermophoresis, and this affinity is significantly reduced when the conserved cyclization sequence is not present. Furthermore, we perform computational kinetic analyses validating the cyclization sequence as the primary driver of this RNA–RNA interaction. Finally, we examined the 3D structure of the interaction using small-angle X-ray scattering, revealing a flexible yet stable interaction. This pathway can be adapted and utilized to study various viral and human long-non-coding RNA–RNA interactions and determine their binding affinities, a critical pharmacological property of designing potential therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.007.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.007.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.008.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.008.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.009.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023/QuickSlide__Mrozowich-2023.009.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkad223"&gt;Investigating RNA-RNA interactions through computational and biophysical analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tyler Mrozowich, Sean Park, Maria Waldl, Amy Henrickson, Scott Tersteeg, Corey R. Nelson, Anneke De Klerk, Borries Demeler, Ivo L. Hofacker, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Trushar R. Patel&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Res.&lt;/em&gt; gkad223 (2023) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkad223"&gt;doi:10.1093/nar/gkad223&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mrozowich-2023.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; |  &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mrozowich-2023__SUPPLEMENT.pdf"&gt;Supplement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="RNA-RNA interaction"></category><category term="non-coding RNA"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="3D"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Strukturierte RNAs in Viren (in German)</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2023/Strukturierte-RNAs-in-Viren/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-03-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2023-03-23:/blog/2023/Strukturierte-RNAs-in-Viren/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this mini-review we discuss the concept of RNA structure conservation in viruses, using exoribonuclease-resistant RNAs from flaviviruses as prominent examples&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Schematic representation of xrRNA exoribonuclease stalling" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Ochsenreiter-2023.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exoribonuclease-resistant RNAs are a type of RNA molecule that possess unique properties in the 3' untranslated region (3'UTR) of flaviviruses, a family of RNA viruses that includes notorious pathogens such as dengue virus and Zika virus. The 3'UTR is a non-coding region of the viral RNA genome that plays crucial roles in viral replication and immune evasion. Exoribonucleases are cellular enzymes that degrade RNA molecules, including viral RNA, as part of the host's antiviral defense mechanism. However, some flaviviruses have evolved to contain specific sequences in their 3'UTR that confer resistance to exoribonuclease degradation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These exoribonuclease-resistant RNAs (xrRNAs) in the 3'UTR of flaviviruses have gained attention as potential therapeutic targets for RNA-based antiviral strategies. By utilizing the unique properties of xrRNAs, we can design RNA molecules that mimic the viral sequences in a synthetic biology context. Utilizing the distinctive features of exoribonuclease-resistant RNAs represents a novel approach in the development of antiviral RNA therapeutics, and may serve as a regulatory tool for future mRNA vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this mini-review, we delve into the biophysical principles underlying exoribonuclease-resistant RNAs, and elucidate their potential applications in innovative RNA therapeutics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work relevant for a One Health systemic view as it underscores the interconnectedness of human, animal, and environmental health. The study delves into the conservation of RNA structures in viruses like dengue and Zika, which are transmitted by mosquitoes. By exploring the potential of xrRNAs as therapeutic targets, the research paves the way for the development of novel, broad-spectrum antiviral strategies that can address disease control and prevention across multiple levels of the ecosystem. Ultimately, this aligns with the One Health approach by acknowledging and addressing the intricate relationships between different facets of health within our ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Ochsenreiter-2023.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Ochsenreiter-2023.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evolutionarily conserved RNAs in untranslated regions are key regulators of the viral life cycle. Exoribonuclease-resistant RNAs (xrRNAs) are particularly interesting examples of structurally conserved elements because they actively dysregulate the messenger RNA (mRNA) degradation machinery of host cells, thereby mediating viral pathogenicity. We review the principles of RNA structure conservation in viruses and discuss potential applications of xrRNAs in synthetic biology and future mRNA vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2023.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://www.biospektrum.de/magazinartikel/strukturierte-rnas-viren"&gt;Strukturierte RNAs in Viren&lt;/a&gt; (in German)&lt;br /&gt;
Roman Ochsenreiter, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Biospektrum&lt;/em&gt; 29(2):156-158 (2023) | | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://www.biospektrum.de/magazinartikel/strukturierte-rnas-viren"&gt;doi:10.1007/s12268-023-1907-x&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Ochsenreiter-2023.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="RNA design"></category><category term="xrRNA"></category><category term="synthetic biology"></category></entry><entry><title>The link between mRNA vaccine design and barbeque optimization</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2022/The-link-between-mRNA-vaccine-design-and-barbeque-optimization/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2022-11-18:/blog/2022/The-link-between-mRNA-vaccine-design-and-barbeque-optimization/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The rational design of vaccine mRNAs and barbeque share common traits: Both require extensive optimization and benefit from experience&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been discussing questions around the interface of RNA bioinformatics and Data with &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jonasrashedi/"&gt;Jonas Rashedi&lt;/a&gt; in his &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/my-data-is-better-than-yours/"&gt;My Data is better than yours&lt;/a&gt; podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="m-button"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/y4ILL_GviGI" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="outreach"></category><category term="RNA design"></category><category term="synthetic biology"></category></entry><entry><title>Musashi-1 RNA-binding protein's role in RNA recognition</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2022/Theoretical-studies-on-RNA-recognition-by-Musashi1-RNA-binding-protein/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2022-07-26:/blog/2022/Theoretical-studies-on-RNA-recognition-by-Musashi1-RNA-binding-protein/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this contribution we study the association complexes of the RNA-binding protein Musashi-1 with different RNA motifs, using molecular dynamics simulations&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Association complexes of Musashi-1 RBD1 and RBD2 with the canonical target RNA GUAGU" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Darai-2022.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musashi-1 (MSI1), an RNA-binding protein, plays a pivotal role in maintaining and self-renewal of neural progenitor and stem cells. Intriguingly, it has been demonstrated to enhance Zika virus (ZIKV) replication, emphasizing the significance of MSI1:RNA complexes in ZIKV-induced neurotropism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study, we employ computational modeling to assess the association complexes formed between the RNA-binding protein MSI1 and various target RNAs. MSI1 has two RNA-binding domains, each displaying distinct affinities for binding single-stranded RNA molecules. Utilizing molecular dynamics simulations alongside binding free energy calculations, we delve into the intricacies of MSI1:RNA complexes. This investigation holds the key to unraveling MSI1's role in congenital neuropathology, notably microcephaly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collaborating with esteemed researchers Thanyada Rungrotmongkol and Nitchakan Darai from Chulalongkorn University, as well as Peter Wolschann from Universität Wien, this study advances our understanding of RNA-protein interactions with profound implications for both biology and disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Darai-2022.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Darai-2022.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Musashi (MSI) family of RNA-binding proteins, comprising the two homologs Musashi-1 (MSI1) and Musashi-2 (MSI2), typically regulates translation and is involved in cell proliferation and tumorigenesis. MSI proteins contain two ribonucleoprotein-like RNA-binding domains, RBD1 and RBD2, that bind single-stranded RNA motifs with a central UAG trinucleotide with high affinity and specificity. The finding that MSI also promotes the replication of Zika virus, a neurotropic Flavivirus, has triggered further investigations of the biochemical principles behind MSI–RNA interactions. However, a detailed molecular understanding of the specificity of MSI RBD1/2 interaction with RNA is still missing. Here, we performed computational studies of MSI1–RNA association complexes, investigating different RNA pentamer motifs using molecular dynamics simulations with binding free energy calculations based on the solvated interaction energy method. Simulations with Alphafold2 suggest that predicted MSI protein structures are highly similar to experimentally determined structures. The binding free energies show that two out of four RNA pentamers exhibit a considerably higher binding affinity to MSI1 RBD1 and RBD2, respectively. The obtained structural information on MSI1 RBD1 and RBD2 will be useful for a detailed functional and mechanistic understanding of this type of RNA–protein interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-16252-w"&gt;Theoretical studies on RNA recognition by Musashi 1 RNA–binding protein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nitchakan Darai, Panupong Mahalapbutr, Peter Wolschann, Vannajan Sanghiran Lee, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolﬁnger&lt;/span&gt;, Thanyada Rungrotmongkol&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sci. Rep.&lt;/em&gt; 12:12137 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-16252-w"&gt;doi:10.1038/s41598-022-16252-w&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Darai-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2019/Musashi-Binding-Elements-in-Zika-and-Related-Flavivirus-3UTRs-A-Comparative-Study-in-Silico/"&gt;Musashi Binding Elements in Zika and Related Flavivirus 3’UTRs: A Comparative Study in Silico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Adriano de Bernardi Schneider, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sci. Rep.&lt;/em&gt; 9(1):6911 (2019) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-43390-5"&gt;doi:10.1038/s41598-019-43390-5&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/deBernardiSchneider-2019a.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2023/blog/2023-06-09-A-Structural-Refinement-Technique-for-Protein-RNA-Complexes-Using-Combination-of-AI-based-Modeling-and-Flexible-Docking-A-Study-of-Musashi-1-Protein/"&gt;A Structural Refinement Technique for Protein-RNA Complexes Using a Combination of AI-based Modeling and Flexible Docking: A Study of Musashi-1 Protein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nitchakan Darai, Kowit Hengphasatporn, Peter Wolschann, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Yasuteru Shigeta, Thanyada Rungrotmongkol, Ryuhei Harada&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;B. Chem. Soc. Jpn.&lt;/em&gt; 96(7):677–685 (2023) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1246/bcsj.20230092"&gt;doi:10.1246/bcsj.20230092&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Darai-2023.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="3D"></category><category term="RNA-Protein interaction"></category><category term="AI"></category></entry><entry><title>Hfq, Crc, and antibiotic resistance in P. aeruginosa</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2022/Rewiring-of-Gene-Expression-in-Pseudomonas-aeruginosa/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2022-06-23:/blog/2022/Rewiring-of-Gene-Expression-in-Pseudomonas-aeruginosa/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here we study carbon catabolite repression (CCR) and its impact on antibiotic susceptibility in Pseudomonas aeruginosa&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Schematic of the mexGHI-opmD operon downregulation by Hfq during carbon catabolite repression" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Rozner-2022.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study on Pseudomonas aeruginosa underscores the interplay between microbial metabolism and antibiotic resistance, which has implications for human, animal, and environmental health. The observed link between carbon catabolite repression (CCR) and antibiotic susceptibility suggests that the microbial response to environmental nutrients can impact the efficacy of antibiotics. This insight is crucial as antibiotic-resistant strains can pose threats to both human healthcare and animal husbandry. Understanding such regulatory mechanisms can guide the development of targeted interventions, aligning with the One Health approach that seeks to optimize health outcomes across different domains of the ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Rozner-2022.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Rozner-2022.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Pseudomonas aeruginosa, the RNA chaperone Hfq and the catabolite repression protein Crc act in concert to regulate numerous genes during carbon catabolite repression (CCR). After alleviation of CCR, the RNA CrcZ sequesters Hfq/Crc, which leads to a rewiring of gene expression to ensure the consumption of less preferred carbon and nitrogen sources. Here, we performed a multiomics approach by assessing the transcriptome, translatome, and proteome in parallel in P. aeruginosa strain O1 during and after relief of CCR. As Hfq function is impeded by the RNA CrcZ upon relief of CCR, and Hfq is known to impact antibiotic susceptibility in P. aeruginosa, emphasis was laid on links between CCR and antibiotic susceptibility. To this end, we show that the mexGHI-opmD operon encoding an efflux pump for the antibiotic norfloxacin and the virulence factor 5-Methyl-phenazine is upregulated after alleviation of CCR, resulting in a decreased susceptibility to the antibiotic norfloxacin. A model for indirect regulation of the mexGHI-opmD operon by Hfq is presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.919539"&gt;Rewiring of Gene Expression in Pseudomonas aeruginosa During Diauxic Growth Reveals an Indirect Regulation of the MexGHI-OpmD Efflux Pump by Hfq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Marlena Rozner, Ella Nukarinen, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Fabian Amman, Wolfram Weckwerth, Udo Blaesi, Elisabeth Sonnleitner&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Front. Microbiol.&lt;/em&gt; (2022) 13:919539 | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.919539"&gt;doi:10.3389/fmicb.2022.919539&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Rozner-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="bacteria"></category><category term="NGS"></category><category term="One Health"></category></entry><entry><title>Japanese encephalitis virus genome cyclization is kinetically driven</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2022/Cyclization-studies-of-Japanese-encephalitis-virus-non-coding-RNA-terminal-regions/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-02-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2022-02-03:/blog/2022/Cyclization-studies-of-Japanese-encephalitis-virus-non-coding-RNA-terminal-regions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This study uses biophysical and bioinformatics methods to assess the long-range RNA-RNA interaction between terminal regions of Japanese encephalitis virus&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Now published in Nucleic Acids Research:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2023/Investigating-RNA-RNA-interactions-through-computational-and-biophysical-analysis/"&gt;Investigating RNA-RNA interactions through computational and biophysical analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tyler Mrozowich, Sean Park, Maria Waldl, Amy Henrickson, Scott Tersteeg, Corey R. Nelson, Anneke De Klerk, Borries Demeler, Ivo L. Hofacker, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Trushar R. Patel&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Res.&lt;/em&gt; gkad223 (2023) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkad223"&gt;doi:10.1093/nar/gkad223&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mrozowich-2023.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; |  &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mrozowich-2023__SUPPLEMENT.pdf"&gt;Supplement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many flaviviruses such as Dengue and West Nile virus undergo essential long-range interactions of their 5’ and 3’ terminal regions (TRs), mediated by a conserved complementary cyclization sequence. However, we lack insights into such long-range interactions for the Japanese Encephalitis virus (JEV). Here, we utilized an extensive, multi-faceted approach involving computational and biophysical tools. We performed multi-angle light scattering (SEC-MALS) to determine absolute molecular weights of JEV TRs, and their complex concluding they form a 1:1 complex and corroborated this interaction using analytical ultracentrifugation (AUC). The microscale thermophoresis (MST) experiments demonstrated that the 5’ and 3’ TR of JEV interact with nM affinity, which is significantly reduced without the conserved cyclization sequence. To our knowledge, this is the first study representing the application of three key biophysical methods (AUC, MST and SEC-MALS) to study RNA-RNA interactions. Furthermore, we performed computational kinetic analyses corroborating our MST studies showing the essential role of the cyclization sequence in the RNA-RNA interaction. The binding affinity of this biologically critical event is a vital pharmacological feature that can influence potential competitive inhibition by therapeutics. This evidence can also influence pharmaceutical interventions aimed at inhibiting the conserved flavivirus cyclization, thus, interrupting replication across the flavivirus family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.02.01.478553"&gt;Cyclization studies of Japanese encephalitis virus non-coding RNA terminal regions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tyler Mrozowich,  Sean M. Park,  Maria Waldl,  Amy Henrickson,  Corey R. Nelson,  Borries Demeler,  Ivo L. Hofacker,  Michael T. Wolfinger, Trushar R. Patel&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt; 2022.02.01.478553 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.02.01.478553"&gt;doi: 10.1101/2022.02.01.478553&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mrozovich-2022__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="RNA-RNA interaction"></category><category term="non-coding RNA"></category><category term="3D"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Biophysical characterisation of human lincRNA-p21 Alu inverted repeats</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2022/Biophysical-Characterisation-of-Human-LincRNA-p21-Sense-and-Antisense-Alu-Inverted-Repeats/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2022-01-20:/blog/2022/Biophysical-Characterisation-of-Human-LincRNA-p21-Sense-and-Antisense-Alu-Inverted-Repeats/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this study we determine the tertiary structure of human LincRNA-p21 Alu Inverted Repeats with biophysical and computational approaches&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/DSouza-2022.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/DSouza-2022.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human Long Intergenic Noncoding RNA-p21 (LincRNA-p21) is a regulatory noncoding RNA that plays an important role in promoting apoptosis. LincRNA-p21 is also critical in down-regulating many p53 target genes through its interaction with a p53 repressive complex. The interaction between LincRNA-p21 and the repressive complex is likely dependent on the RNA tertiary structure. Previous studies have determined the two-dimensional secondary structures of the sense and antisense human LincRNA-p21 AluSx1 IRs using SHAPE. However, there were no insights into its three-dimensional structure. Therefore, we in vitro transcribed the sense and antisense regions of LincRNA-p21 AluSx1 Inverted Repeats (IRs) and performed analytical ultracentrifugation, size exclusion chromatography, light scattering, and small angle X-ray scattering (SAXS) studies. Based on these studies, we determined low-resolution, three-dimensional structures of sense and antisense LincRNA-p21. By adapting previously known two-dimensional information, we calculated their sense and antisense high-resolution models and determined that they agree with the low-resolution structures determined using SAXS. Thus, our integrated approach provides insights into the structure of LincRNA-p21 Alu IRs. Our study also offers a viable pipeline for combining the secondary structure information with biophysical and computational studies to obtain high-resolution atomistic models for long noncoding RNAs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkac414"&gt;Biophysical Characterisation of Human LincRNA-p21 Sense and Antisense Alu Inverted Repeats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michael H. D’Souza, Tyler Mrozowich, Maulik D. Badmalia, Mitchell Geeraert, Angela Frederickson, Amy Henrickson, Borries Demeler, Michael T. Wolfinger, Trushar R. Patel&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Nucleic Acids Res.&lt;/em&gt; gkac414 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkac414"&gt;doi:10.1093/nar/gkac414&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/DSouza-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="3D"></category><category term="non-coding RNA"></category></entry><entry><title>RNA structure conservation and molecular epidemiology of TBEV</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Evolutionary-traits-of-Tick-borne-encephalitis-virus-Pervasive-non-coding-RNA-structure-conservation-and-molecular-epidemiology/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2021-12-17:/blog/2021/Evolutionary-traits-of-Tick-borne-encephalitis-virus-Pervasive-non-coding-RNA-structure-conservation-and-molecular-epidemiology/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we study the molecular epidemiology and RNA structureome diversity of tick-borne encephalitis virus (TBEV). Moreover, we propose a unified picture of pervasive non-coding RNA structure conservation across all known TBEV subtypes&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Annotated 3'UTR of representative tick-borne encephalitis virus (TBEV) strains" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Kutschera-2022.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research aimed to understand the RNA structure conservation in the 3'UTR region of Tick-Borne Encephalitis Virus (TBEV), a flavivirus endemic in parts of Europe and Asia. The study revealed that the TBEV 3’UTRs contain two domains: a highly conserved core domain at the 3’end, and a variable region upstream. The core domain has five structured ncRNA elements, two of which are associated with virulence and virus replication. The variable region, responsible for the differences in genome lengths across subtypes, contains between two and four distinct structural elements. We show that the TBEV 3′ architectural diversity is realized by a combination of a restricted pool of eight structural and one non-structural element, suggesting that the observed 3′UTR variability is driven by structural, rather than sequence conservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study also introduces &lt;a href="https://nextstrain.org/groups/ViennaRNA/TBEVnext"&gt;TBEVnext&lt;/a&gt;, a dataset revealing spatiotemporal and phylodynamic characteristics of TBEV global spread. &lt;a href="https://nextstrain.org/groups/ViennaRNA/TBEVnext"&gt;TBEVnext&lt;/a&gt; includes various TBEV subtypes and shows no strict association between TBEV subtypes and geographic occurrence. A timed phylogenetic tree inferred from this data provides insights into the ecological aspects of the global virus spread and unique properties of different strains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a One Health perspective, the findings of the study underscore the importance of understanding the intricate relationships between the virus's genetic makeup and its spread and adaptability across different regions and host species. By identifying the conserved and variable elements in TBEV 3’UTRs, researchers can gain insights into the mechanisms of virulence and replication, potentially guiding the development of targeted interventions. Additionally, the comprehensive view on the global spread of TBEV provided by &lt;a href="https://nextstrain.org/groups/ViennaRNA/TBEVnext"&gt;TBEVnext&lt;/a&gt; emphasizes the need for integrated approaches that consider the interconnectedness of human, animal, and environmental health to effectively monitor and control such zoonotic diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Kutschera-2022.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Kutschera-2022.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick-borne encephalitis virus (TBEV) is the etiological agent of tick-borne encephalitis, an infectious disease of the central nervous system that is often associated with severe sequelae in humans. While TBEV is typically classified into three subtypes, recent evidence suggests a more varied range of TBEV subtypes and lineages that differ substantially in their 3’UTR architecture. Building on comparative genomics approaches and thermodynamic modelling, we characterize the TBEV 3’UTR structureome diversity and propose a unified picture of pervasive non-coding RNA (ncRNA) structure conservation. Moreover, we provide an updated phylogeny of TBEV, building on more than 220 publicly available complete genomes, and investigate the molecular epidemiology and phylodynamics with Nextstrain, a web-based visualization framework for real-time pathogen evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.007.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.007.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.008.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.008.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ve/veac051"&gt;Evolutionary traits of Tick-borne encephalitis virus: Pervasive non-coding RNA structure conservation and molecular epidemiology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lena S. Kutschera, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Virus Evol.&lt;/em&gt; (8):1 veac051 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ve/veac051"&gt;doi: 10.1093/ve/veac051&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Kutschera-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; |  &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Kutschera-2022__SupplementaryData.pdf"&gt;Supplementary data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2019/Functional_RNA_Structures_in_the_three_prime_UTR_of_Flaviviruses/"&gt;Functional RNA Structures in the 3’UTR of Tick-Borne, Insect-Specific and No Known Vector Flaviviruses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Roman Ochsenreiter, Ivo L. Hofacker, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Viruses&lt;/em&gt; 11:298 (2019) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/v11030298"&gt;doi:10.3390/v11030298&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Ochsenreiter-2019.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Functional-RNA-Structures-in-the-3UTR-of-Mosquito-Borne-Flaviviruses/"&gt;Functional RNA Structures in the 3’UTR of Mosquito-Borne Flaviviruses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Roman Ochsenreiter, Ivo L. Hofacker&lt;br /&gt;
In &lt;em&gt;Virus Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Dmitrij Frishman and Manja Marz, pp65–100. Chapman and Hall/CRC Press (2021) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1201/9781003097679-5"&gt;doi:10.1201/9781003097679-5&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2021.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="non-coding RNA"></category><category term="One Health"></category><category term="xrRNA"></category><category term="molecular epidemiology"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Deep learning methods are unable to predict RNA secondary structures</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Caveats-to-deep-learning-approaches-to-RNA-secondary-structure-prediction/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2021-12-16:/blog/2021/Caveats-to-deep-learning-approaches-to-RNA-secondary-structure-prediction/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;RNA structure prediction might seem like an ideal fit for machine learning, but it's more challenging than you might think. In this paper, we explore these difficulties by using synthetic data generated by ViennaRNA's RNAfold, offering a controlled environment to study how neural networks handle RNA secondary structure prediction. What we found suggests that the limitations seen in artificial settings can directly translate to real-world data, raising important questions about the effectiveness of current machine learning approaches in this field.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Input/output encoding for predicting RNA paired/unpaired status using a BLSTM" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Flamm-2022.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the major issues we discovered is that many published AI models for RNA structure prediction rely on highly biased training sets. This bias significantly impacts the accuracy of predictions when the models are tested on RNA sequences outside of their training set. By using a technique known as inverse RNA folding—where we generate sequences that match specific structures—we created synthetic data with the same kind of bias found in these deep learning models. When we trained a neural network on this biased data, it performed well on new sequences that folded into familiar structures. However, when faced with sequences forming novel structures, the performance dropped drastically. This shows that while the network could generalize to new sequences, it struggled to predict new or unseen structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more surprising is that many deep learning methods trained on unbiased data couldn't even reliably predict base pairing—a fundamental aspect of RNA structure that's simpler than the full RNA folding problem. Additionally, certain models, such as BLSTMs, predicted structural features like pseudoknots and base triplets, which don’t even appear in the ViennaRNA RNAfold ground truth. This mismatch between model output and reality underscores the limitations of these approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings reveal significant gaps in current machine learning models for RNA structure prediction and highlight the need for more robust training methods. These insights could drive future improvements in how AI is applied to RNA biology, especially for tackling more complex tasks like RNA folding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Flamm-2022.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Flamm-2022.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning (ML) and in particular deep learning techniques have gained popularity for predicting structures from biopolymer sequences. An interesting case is the prediction of RNA secondary structures, where well established biophysics based methods exist. These methods even yield exact solutions under certain simplifying assumptions. Nevertheless, the accuracy of these classical methods is limited and has seen little improvement over the last decade. This makes it an attractive target for machine learning and consequently several deep learning models have been proposed in recent years. In this contribution we discuss limitations of current approaches, in particular due to biases in the training data. Furthermore, we propose to study capabilities and limitations of ML models by first applying them on synthetic data that can not only be generated in arbitrary amounts, but are also guaranteed to be free of biases. We apply this idea by testing several ML models of varying complexity. Finally, we show that the best models are capable of capturing many, but not all, properties of RNA secondary structures. Most severely, the number of predicted base pairs scales quadratically with sequence length, even though a secondary structure can only accommodate a linear number of pairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.007.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.007.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.008.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022/QuickSlide__Flamm-2022.008.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fbinf.2022.835422"&gt;Caveats to deep learning approaches to RNA secondary structure prediction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Christoph Flamm, Julia Wielach, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Stefan Badelt, Ronny Lorenz, Ivo L. Hofacker&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Front. Bioinform.&lt;/em&gt; 2:835422 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fbinf.2022.835422"&gt;doi:10.3389/fbinf.2022.835422&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Flamm-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="ViennaRNA"></category><category term="AI"></category></entry><entry><title>Functional RNA structures in the 3'UTR of Mosquito-Borne Flaviviruses</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Functional-RNA-Structures-in-the-3UTR-of-Mosquito-Borne-Flaviviruses/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-11-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2021-09-02:/blog/2021/Functional-RNA-Structures-in-the-3UTR-of-Mosquito-Borne-Flaviviruses/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The 3'UTR of Mosquito-Borne Flaviviruses (MBF) contain evolutionarily conserved functional elements, such as exoribonuclease-resistant RNAs (xrRNAs), dumbbell elements or terminal stem-loops. In this contribution we describe, annotate, and compare these elements within different serological groups of MBF&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Consenus RNA secondary sructures of evolutionary conserved elements in flavivirus 3'UTRs" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Wolfinger-2021.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mosquito-borne flaviviruses (MBF) are responsible for millions of infections in humans and animals each year, posing a significant public health threat. These viruses belong to the Flavivirus family, characterized by their enveloped, non-segmented, single-stranded (+)-sense RNA genome. This genome, known as gRNA, is about 10-12 kilobases long and contains a single open reading frame (ORF) flanked by highly structured untranslated regions (UTRs) at both ends. The UTRs play a crucial role in regulating the viral life cycle by mediating essential processes like genome cyclization, replication, and immune system evasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the heart of these regulatory functions are conserved RNA elements within the flavivirus UTRs. One of the best-studied elements is the exoribonuclease-resistant RNA (xrRNA), which stalls host exoribonucleases like Xrn1. By blocking Xrn1's progression toward the viral 3' end, xrRNAs protect downstream nucleotides from degradation, ensuring the stability of the viral RNA. While xrRNAs are well understood, MBF contain several other conserved RNA structures in their UTRs whose functions remain unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To deepen our understanding of RNA structure conservation in MBF, we recently conducted a comparative genomics screen, focusing on the 3' UTR of all known mosquito-borne flaviviruses. Our findings shed light on the evolutionary pressures that shape these RNA structures and reveal potential new regulatory elements that could be critical to the virus’s survival and pathogenicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research not only expands our knowledge of how flaviviruses manipulate host cells but also opens up new avenues for antiviral strategies targeting these conserved RNA elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2021.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2021.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent experimental evidence revealed a thorough understanding of the involvement of functional RNA elements in the 3’ untranslated regions (UTRs) of flaviviruses with virus tropism. Comparative genomics and thermodynamic modelling allow for the prediction and functional characterization of homologous structures in phylogenetically related viruses. We provide here a comprehensive overview of evolutionarily conserved RNAs in the 3’UTRs of mosquito-borne flaviviruses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.007.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.007.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.008.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.008.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.009.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.009.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.010.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.010.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.011.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.011.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.012.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.012.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/chapters/edit/10.1201/9781003097679-5/functional-rna-structures-3%E2%80%B2-utr-mosquito-borne-flaviviruses-michael-wolfinger-roman-ochsenreiter-ivo-hofacker"&gt;Functional RNA Structures in the 3’UTR of Mosquito-Borne Flaviviruses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Michael T. Wolfinger, Roman Ochsenreiter, Ivo L. Hofacker&lt;br /&gt;
In &lt;em&gt;Virus Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Dmitrij Frishman and Manja Marz, pp65–100. Chapman and Hall/CRC Press (2021) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1201/9781003097679-5"&gt;doi: 10.1201/9781003097679-5&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2021.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2019/Functional_RNA_Structures_in_the_three_prime_UTR_of_Flaviviruses/"&gt;Functional RNA Structures in the 3’UTR of Tick-Borne, Insect-Specific and No Known Vector Flaviviruses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Roman Ochsenreiter, Ivo L. Hofacker, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Viruses&lt;/em&gt; 11:298 (2019) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/v11030298"&gt;doi:10.3390/v11030298&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Ochsenreiter-2019.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Evolutionary-traits-of-Tick-borne-encephalitis-virus-Pervasive-non-coding-RNA-structure-conservation-and-molecular-epidemiology/"&gt;Evolutionary traits of Tick-borne encephalitis virus: Pervasive non-coding RNA structure conservation and molecular epidemiology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lena S. Kutschera, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Virus Evol.&lt;/em&gt; (8):1 veac051 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ve/veac051"&gt;doi:10.1093/ve/veac051&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Kutschera-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="non-coding RNA"></category><category term="xrRNA"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>BVDV IRES RNA in focus: A game changer for livestock health</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Insights-into-the-secondary-and-tertiary-structure-of-the-Bovine-Viral-Diarrhea-Virus-Internal-Ribosome-Entry-Site/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-11-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2021-05-15:/blog/2021/Insights-into-the-secondary-and-tertiary-structure-of-the-Bovine-Viral-Diarrhea-Virus-Internal-Ribosome-Entry-Site/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here we characterize a pseudoknot in the 5'UTR Internal Ribosome Entry Site (IRES) of Bovine Viral Diarrhea Virus (BVDV) using SHAPE-guided RNA structure probing and computational modelling of secondary and tertiary structures&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="3D structure prediction of the BVDV IRES region" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Gosavi-2022.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RNA viruses have long fascinated researchers with their ability to adapt and evolve using minimal genetic material. Among these viruses, Bovine Viral Diarrhea Virus (BVDV) stands out as a significant veterinary pathogen, causing substantial economic losses in the livestock industry worldwide. Understanding the molecular mechanisms behind the replication cycle of BVDV is crucial for developing effective strategies to combat this virus. In our recently published paper, we delve into the intricacies of BVDV's RNA structure, shedding light on its critical role in viral translation. Here, we aim to provide an accessible explanation of our findings for both experts and non-virologists and emphasize the relevance of our research to the &lt;em&gt;One Health System&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BVDV belongs to the Pestivirus genus, a group of viruses known for their economic impact on the livestock industry. Like other RNA viruses, BVDV employs resource-efficient molecular strategies to optimize its replication cycle. Central to this process is the Internal Ribosome Entry Site (IRES) located within the virus's 5' Untranslated Region (UTR). The IRES is a complex structural domain that controls cap-independent translation, a crucial step in viral infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our study focused on unraveling the intricate secondary and tertiary structure of BVDV IRES RNA. We used RNA structural probing methods and computational 3D modeling to gain insights into the structural arrangement of this critical RNA component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research revealed that BVDV IRES RNA consists of three major structural domains (I-III), each containing distinct motifs, such as hairpins and stems, interspersed among less structurally constrained regions. While our model aligned with previous secondary structure models for BVDV strains, we identified an alternative folding pattern in domain II. This structural flexibility in domain II was supported by thermodynamic parameters, highlighting the dynamic nature of BVDV IRES RNA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most significant discovery in our study pertains to domain III, which exhibited high structural stability. It includes single-stranded regions and a pseudoknot, a structural element crucial for viral translation. Our 3D modeling revealed quasi-coaxial stacking between specific motifs in domain III, providing insight into the stability of the IRES pseudoknot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous studies had suggested the presence of a pseudoknot in BVDV IRES RNA, but our research provided computational evidence supporting its crucial role. We conducted a comprehensive analysis of BVDV IRES RNA sequences from different genotypes and identified statistically significant covariation in 22 base pairs, including the pseudoknot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings have far-reaching implications in combating BVDV and related viruses. The similarities between BVDV and Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) IRES RNAs suggest that strategies developed to target HCV IRES RNA could potentially be applied to interfere with BVDV replication. This includes the identification of small molecule inhibitors, antisense oligonucleotides, and ribozymes to disrupt the IRES RNA, preventing the binding of translational factors and ultimately inhibiting viral replication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, our research has unveiled the structural intricacies of BVDV IRES RNA, shedding light on its role in viral translation. This knowledge opens up exciting possibilities for the development of targeted therapies against BVDV and related viruses, contributing to the &lt;em&gt;One Health&lt;/em&gt; System's mission of protecting both human and animal health. As we continue to delve deeper into the molecular mechanisms of these pathogens, we move one step closer to mitigating the threats they pose to our global community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Gosavi-2022.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Gosavi-2022.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internal Ribosome Entry Site (IRES) RNA of Bovine viral diarrhea virus (BVDV), an economically significant Pestivirus, is required for the cap-independent translation of viral genomic RNA. Thus, it is essential for viral replication and pathogenesis. We applied a combination of high-throughput biochemical RNA structure probing (SHAPE-MaP) and in silico modeling approaches to gain insight into the secondary and tertiary structures of BVDV IRES RNA. Our study demonstrated that BVDV IRES RNA forms in solution a modular architecture composed of three distinct structural domains (I-III). Two regions within domain III are engaged in tertiary interactions to form an H-type pseudoknot. Computational modeling of the pseudoknot motif provided a fine-grained picture of the tertiary structure and local arrangement of helices in the BVDV IRES. Furthermore, comparative genomics and consensus structure predictions revealed that the pseudoknot is evolutionarily conserved among many Pestivirus species. These studies provide detailed insight into the structural arrangement of BVDV IRES RNA H-type pseudoknot and encompassing motifs that likely contribute to the optimal functionality of viral cap-independent translation element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.007.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022/QuickSlide__Gosavi-2022.007.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1080/15476286.2022.2058818"&gt;Insights into the secondary and tertiary structure of the Bovine Viral Diarrhea Virus Internal Ribosome Entry Site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Devadatta Gosavi, Iwona Wower, Irene K Beckmann, Ivo L Hofacker, Jacek Wower, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Joanna Sztuba-Solinska&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;RNA Biol.&lt;/em&gt; 19(1) 496-506 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1080/15476286.2022.2058818"&gt;doi:10.1080/15476286.2022.2058818&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Gosavi-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="3D"></category><category term="SHAPE"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="non-coding RNA"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Mpulungu Virus: A glimpse into Africa's novel tick-borne flavivirus</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Mpulungu_Virus_is_a_novel_tick_flavivirus_from_Africa/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2021-03-01:/blog/2021/Mpulungu_Virus_is_a_novel_tick_flavivirus_from_Africa/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The discovery of Mpulungu virus (MPFV), a novel tick-borne flavivirus in Zambia, expands our understanding of the geographical distribution and genetic diversity of flaviviruses across Africa. This study delves into the genetic details of MPFV, suggesting its potential to infect vertebrate hosts and underscoring the importance of a One Health approach in addressing emerging infectious diseases&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Exoribonuclease-resistant RNAs (xrRNAs) in the 3'UTR of Mpulungu virus" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Harima-2021.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We report the discovery of Mpulungu virus (MPFV), a novel tick flavivirus, identified in a tick species from Zambia. The complete genome sequence of MPFV was determined and found to be closely related to the Ngoye virus from Senegal, suggesting that this group of viruses may be widespread across Africa. This expands the known geographical distribution and genetic diversity of flaviviruses. Despite unsuccessful attempts to isolate MPFV in cell culture and neonatal mice, the study employed a predictive analysis based on dinucleotide ratios, which suggested that MPFV might infect vertebrate hosts similar to other tick-borne flaviviruses (TBFVs), potentially posing a public health risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study further delved into the genetic details of MPFV, focusing on the untranslated regions (UTRs) of the viral genome that are crucial for viral translation and replication. The 5′-UTR of MPFV showed a typical flavivirus structure, suggesting similar RNA synthesis processes. However, the 3′-UTR displayed some unique characteristics, differing from known TBFVs in terms of sequence composition, length, and secondary structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study identified two exoribonuclease-resistant RNA (xrRNA) structures in the 3′-UTR of MPFV that achieve resistance to an enzyme called Xrn1, which is typically involved in degrading viral RNA. The presence of multiple xrRNA structures in MPFV's 3′-UTR was also noted to potentially contribute to the production of subgenomic flavivirus RNA (sfRNA). Past studies have suggested that xrRNA structures play a significant role in the viral life cycle and pathogenicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discovery of MPFV in Zambia and its potential relation to Ngoye virus in Senegal points towards a need for comprehensive surveillance of flaviviruses across diverse ecosystems. By identifying and understanding the genetic makeup and host range of such viruses, preventive measures can be implemented to mitigate potential public health risks. This study highlights the necessity of integrated efforts and knowledge sharing among health professionals, veterinarians, and environmental scientists to enhance our preparedness and response to emerging infectious diseases. In light of these findings, employing the One Health approach becomes imperative to comprehensively address and understand the complexities and potential implications of emerging flaviviruses like MPFV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Harima-2021.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Harima-2021.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tick-borne flaviviruses (TBFVs) infect mammalian hosts through tick bites and can cause various serious illnesses, such as encephalitis and hemorrhagic fevers, both in humans and animals. Despite their importance to public health, there is limited epidemiological information on TBFV infection in Africa. Herein, we report that a novel flavivirus, Mpulungu flavivirus (MPFV), was discovered in a Rhipicephalus muhsamae tick in Zambia. MPFV was found to be genetically related to Ngoye virus detected in ticks in Senegal, and these viruses formed a unique lineage in the genus Flavivirus. Analyses of dinucleotide contents of flaviviruses indicated that MPFV was similar to those of other TBFVs with a typical vertebrate genome signature, suggesting that MPFV may infect vertebrate hosts. Bioinformatic analyses of the secondary structures in the 3′-untranslated regions (UTRs) revealed that MPFV exhibited unique exoribonuclease-resistant RNA (xrRNA) structures. Utilizing biochemical approaches, we clarified that two xrRNA structures of MPFV in the 3′-UTR could prevent exoribonuclease activity. In summary, our findings provide new information regarding the geographical distribution of TBFV and xrRNA structures in the 3′-UTR of flaviviruses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-84365-9"&gt;An African Tick Flavivirus Forming an Independent Clade Exhibits Unique Exoribonuclease-Resistant RNA Structures in the Genomic 3’-Untranslated Region&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hayato Harima, Yasuko Orba, Shiho Torii, Yongjin Qiu, Masahiro Kajihara, Yoshiki Eto, Naoya Matsuta, Bernard M. Hang’ombe, Yuki Eshita, Kentaro Uemura, Keita Matsuno, Michihito Sasaki, Kentaro Yoshii, Ryo Nakao, William W. Hall, Ayato Takada, Takashi Abe, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Martin Simuunza, Hirofumi Sawa&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sci. Rep.&lt;/em&gt; 11:4883 (2021) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-84365-9"&gt;doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-84365-9&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Harima-2021.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2024/blog/2024-05-29-Xingyang-flavivirus-from-Haemaphysalis-flava-ticks-defines-a-basal-likely-tick-only-Orthoflavivirus-clade/"&gt;Xinyang flavivirus, from Haemaphysalis flava ticks in Henan province, China, defines a basal, likely tick-only flavivirus clade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lan-Lan Wang, Qia Cheng, Natalee D. Newton, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Mahali S. Morgan, Andrii Slonchak, Alexander A. Khromykh, Tian-Yin Cheng, Rhys H. Parry&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;J. Gen. Virol.&lt;/em&gt; 105(5) (2024) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1099/jgv.0.001991"&gt;doi:10.1099/jgv.0.001991&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wang-2024.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="novel viruses"></category><category term="xrRNA"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Molecular epidemiology and RNA structures in Chikungunya virus</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Lineage-specific-RNA-structures-in-Chikungunya-virus/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2021-02-08:/blog/2021/Lineage-specific-RNA-structures-in-Chikungunya-virus/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This research provides a comprehensive analysis of the molecular epidemiology and evolutionary dynamics of Chikungunya virus (CHIKV), uncovering how single nucleotide variants influence viral RNA structures and shape the global spread of the virus&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-col-t-10 m-center-t m-col-s-10 m-center-s m-col-m-6 m-right-m"&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure m-flat"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Enselble properties of a lineage-specific structured RNA in Chikungunya virus" src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/preview/Preview__Spicher-2021.001small.webp" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chikungunya virus, an emerging Alphavirus, causes millions of human infections annually and has witnessed outbreaks in Africa and Asia since the 1950s. The research presented here delves into the molecular epidemiology of CHIKV, revealing how single nucleotide variants can impact the virus's RNA structures. Utilizing more than 1000 publicly available CHIKV genomes, the study provides an interactive phylodynamics dataset using Nextstrain, a tool for real-time tracking of pathogen evolution. The data set, publicly available through &lt;a href="https://nextstrain.org/groups/ViennaRNA/CHIKVnext"&gt;CHIKVnext&lt;/a&gt;, enables the tracking of spatiotemporal and epidemiological aspects of the CHIKV global spread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study addresses genotype/phenotype associations in CHIKV by employing comparative approaches, molecular epidemiology concepts, phylogeny reconstruction, and computational RNA biology. The nucleotide divergence within CHIKV lineages is found to be relatively low, often due to geographical constraints and a limited collection period for newer lineages. However, the divergence between different lineages can be considerable, with the West African lineage showing the highest divergence compared to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This publication questions the current nomenclature of CHIKV lineages, and suggests that a new system, independent of geography, might be more coherent and beneficial for drug and vaccine development. Despite the low divergence in some established lineages, mutations like A226V in E1 can significantly impact the virus's capacity to replicate. The study further highlights the importance of increased surveillance to identify the virus at the time of introduction rather than during a pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research exemplifies the importance of a holistic, interdisciplinary approach in understanding and combating infectious diseases such as CHIKV. The findings, which combine molecular epidemiology and RNA structure prediction, not only pave the way for better diagnostic and treatment methods but also underscore the necessity of a timely response to prevent outbreaks. The One Health approach is particularly pertinent here. By adopting a unified perspective, scientists, healthcare professionals, and policymakers can work together to address the multifaceted challenges posed by CHIKV and similar infectious diseases, ultimately contributing to the well-being of our global ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Spicher-2021.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Spicher-2021.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) is an emerging Alphavirus which causes millions of human infections every year. Outbreaks have been reported in Africa and Asia since the early 1950s, from three CHIKV lineages: West African, East Central South African, and Asian Urban. As new outbreaks occurred in the Americas, individual strains from the known lineages have evolved, creating new monophyletic groups that generated novel geographic-based lineages. Building on a recently updated phylogeny of CHIKV, we report here the availability of an interactive CHIKV phylodynamics dataset, which is based on more than 900 publicly available CHIKV genomes. We provide an interactive view of CHIKV molecular epidemiology built on Nextstrain, a web-based visualization framework for real-time tracking of pathogen evolution. CHIKV molecular epidemiology reveals single nucleotide variants that change the stability and fold of locally stable RNA structures. We propose alternative RNA structure formation in different CHIKV lineages by predicting more than a dozen RNA elements that are subject to perturbation of the structure ensemble upon variation of a single nucleotide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.007.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.007.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.008.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.008.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Lineage-specific-RNA-structures-in-Chikungunya-virus/"&gt;Dynamic Molecular Epidemiology Reveals Lineage-Associated Single-Nucleotide Variants That Alter RNA Structure in Chikungunya Virus &lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thomas Spicher, Markus Delitz, Adriano de Bernardi Schneider, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Genes&lt;/em&gt; 12 (2):239 (2021) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/genes12020239"&gt;doi:10.3390/genes12020239&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Spicher-2021.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2019/Updated-Phylogeny-of-Chikungunya-Virus-Suggests-Lineage-Specific-RNA-Architecture/"&gt;Updated Phylogeny of Chikungunya Virus Suggests Lineage-Specific RNA Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Adriano de Bernardi Schneider, Roman Ochsenreiter, Reilly Hostager, Ivo L. Hofacker, Daniel Janies, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Viruses&lt;/em&gt; 11:798 (2019) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/v11090798"&gt;doi:10.3390/v11090798&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/deBernardiSchneider-2019b.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="One Health"></category><category term="molecular epidemiology"></category><category term="alphavirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Genomic epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 superspreading events in Austria</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2020/blog/2020-12-10-Genomic-Epidemiology-of-Superspreading-Events-in-Austria-Reveals-Mutational-Dynamics-and-Transmission-Properties-of-SARS-CoV-2/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2020-12-10:/blog/2020/blog/2020-12-10-Genomic-Epidemiology-of-Superspreading-Events-in-Austria-Reveals-Mutational-Dynamics-and-Transmission-Properties-of-SARS-CoV-2/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This study shows how superspreading events fueled the first wave of SARS-CoV-2 in Austria. We analyzed viral mutations and traced travel patterns, revealing the impact of superspreading on the course of the outbreak&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="m-button m-primary"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Popa-2020.pdf"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Download PDF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superspreading events shaped the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, and their rapid identification and containment are essential for disease control. Here, we provide a national-scale analysis of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) superspreading during the first wave of infections in Austria, a country that played a major role in initial virus transmissions in Europe. Capitalizing on Austria’s well-developed epidemiological surveillance system, we identified major SARS-CoV-2 clusters during the first wave of infections and performed deep whole-genome sequencing of more than 500 virus samples. Phylogenetic-epidemiological analysis enabled the reconstruction of superspreading events and charts a map of tourism-related viral spread originating from Austria in spring 2020. Moreover, we exploited epidemiologically well-defined clusters to quantify SARS-CoV-2 mutational dynamics, including the observation of low-frequency mutations that progressed to fixation within the infection chain. Time-resolved virus sequencing unveiled viral mutation dynamics within individuals with COVID-19, and epidemiologically validated infector-infectee pairs enabled us to determine an average transmission bottleneck size of 103 SARS-CoV-2 particles. In conclusion, this study illustrates the power of combining epidemiological analysis with deep viral genome sequencing to unravel the spread of SARS-CoV-2 and to gain fundamental insights into mutational dynamics and transmission properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.abe2555"&gt;Genomic Epidemiology of Superspreading Events in Austria Reveals Mutational Dynamics and Transmission Properties of SARS-CoV-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Alexandra Popa, Jakob-Wendelin Genger, Michael D. Nicholson, Thomas Penz, Daniela Schmid, Stephan W Aberle, Benedikt Agerer, Alexander Lercher, Lukas Endler, Henrique Colaco, Mark Smyth, Michael Schuster, Miguel L. Grau, Francisco Martínez-Jiménez, Oriol Pich, Wegene Borena, Erich Pawelka, Zsofia Keszei, Martin Senekowitsch, Jan Laine, Judith H Aberle, Monika Redlberger-Fritz, Mario Karolyi, Alexander Zoufaly, Sabine Maritschnik, Martin Borkovec, Peter Hufnagl, Manfred Nairz, Günter Weiss, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Dorothee von Laer, Giulio Superti-Furga, Nuria Lopez-Bigas, Elisabeth Puchhammer-Stöckl, Franz Allerberger, Franziska Michor, Christoph Bock, Andreas Bergthaler&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sci. Transl. Med.&lt;/em&gt; 12 (573):eabe2555 (2020) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.abe2555"&gt;doi:10.1126/scitranslmed.abe2555&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Popa-2020.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="molecular epidemiology"></category><category term="One Health"></category></entry><entry><title>Chikungunya Virus Phylogeny: Lineage-Specific RNA Structures</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2019/Updated-Phylogeny-of-Chikungunya-Virus-Suggests-Lineage-Specific-RNA-Architecture/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2019-08-29:/blog/2019/Updated-Phylogeny-of-Chikungunya-Virus-Suggests-Lineage-Specific-RNA-Architecture/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this study, we analyzed the evolution and spread of the Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) across Africa by examining 598 whole genome sequences. Our analysis revealed several distinct CHIKV lineages with strong support, providing new insights into the virus's evolutionary history and its movement across regions&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We carried out an in-depth analysis of the virus’s 3’UTR, where we uncovered conserved RNA structures that likely play crucial roles in stabilizing viral RNA and interacting with host proteins. One of our most intriguing findings was the discovery of unique 3’UTR structures specific to certain lineages. These features may help the virus counter host defenses and interact with key cellular proteins, such as the Musashi family of translational regulators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our comprehensive analysis provides valuable insights into the complex evolution and epidemiology of CHIKV. By highlighting lineage-specific traits, we hope this study will pave the way for a deeper understanding of viral genomics and open up new opportunities for targeted interventions. As we continue to explore the intricacies of CHIKV's genetic makeup, our findings represent an important step in the global effort to combat this significant public health threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/deBernardiSchneider-2019b.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/deBernardiSchneider-2019b.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chikungunya virus (CHIKV), a mosquito-borne alphavirus of the family Togaviridae, has recently emerged in the Americas from lineages from two continents: Asia and Africa. Historically, CHIKV circulated as at least four lineages worldwide with both enzootic and epidemic transmission cycles. To understand the recent patterns of emergence and the current status of the CHIKV spread, updated analyses of the viral genetic data and metadata are needed. Here, we performed phylogenetic and comparative genomics screens of CHIKV genomes, taking advantage of the public availability of many recently sequenced isolates. Based on these new data and analyses, we derive a revised phylogeny from nucleotide sequences in coding regions. Using this phylogeny, we uncover the presence of several distinct lineages in Africa that were previously considered a single one. In parallel, we performed thermodynamic modeling of CHIKV untranslated regions (UTRs), which revealed evolutionarily conserved structured and unstructured RNA elements in the 3’UTR. We provide evidence for duplication events in recently emerged American isolates of the Asian CHIKV lineage and propose the existence of a flexible 3’UTR architecture among different CHIKV lineages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.007.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.007.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2019/Updated-Phylogeny-of-Chikungunya-Virus-Suggests-Lineage-Specific-RNA-Architecture/"&gt;Updated Phylogeny of Chikungunya Virus Suggests Lineage-Specific RNA Architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Adriano de Bernardi Schneider, Roman Ochsenreiter, Reilly Hostager, Ivo L. Hofacker, Daniel Janies, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Viruses&lt;/em&gt; 11:798 (2019) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/v11090798"&gt;doi:10.3390/v11090798&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/deBernardiSchneider-2019b.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019b.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Lineage-specific-RNA-structures-in-Chikungunya-virus/"&gt;Dynamic Molecular Epidemiology Reveals Lineage-Associated Single-Nucleotide Variants That Alter RNA Structure in Chikungunya Virus &lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thomas Spicher, Markus Delitz, Adriano de Bernardi Schneider, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Genes&lt;/em&gt; 12 (2):239 (2021) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/genes12020239"&gt;doi:10.3390/genes12020239&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Spicher-2021.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Spicher-2021.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="molecular epidemiology"></category><category term="One Health"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="alphavirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Musashi binding elements in Zika virus 3'UTR</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2019/Musashi-Binding-Elements-in-Zika-and-Related-Flavivirus-3UTRs-A-Comparative-Study-in-Silico/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2019-05-06:/blog/2019/Musashi-Binding-Elements-in-Zika-and-Related-Flavivirus-3UTRs-A-Comparative-Study-in-Silico/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Discovering the characteristic traits of Musashi Binding Elements (MBEs) in Flaviviruses with a Thermodynamic Model&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this study, we investigated how flaviviruses can cause congenital neurological disease by examining the accessibility of a specific binding motif for RNA-binding proteins from the Musashi family in the 3'UTR of flaviviruses. Through evaluating the affinity of different viruses to form RNA-protein complexes, we aimed to understand the role of Musashi proteins in promoting Zika virus replication and inducing congenital neurotropism. Using a well-established biophysical model of RNA structure formation, we conducted computational analysis of the thermodynamic properties of Musashi binding elements. Our findings support the hypothesis that suggest Zika virus (ZIKV) is not the only flavivirus capable of causing severe neuropathology through interaction with the Musashi proteins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/deBernardiSchneider-2019a.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/deBernardiSchneider-2019a.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zika virus (ZIKV) belongs to a class of neurotropic viruses that have the ability to cause congenital infection, which can result in microcephaly or fetal demise. Recently, the RNA-binding protein Musashi-1 (Msi1), which mediates the maintenance and self-renewal of stem cells and acts as a translational regulator, has been associated with promoting ZIKV replication, neurotropism, and pathology. Msi1 predominantly binds to single-stranded motifs in the 3′ untranslated region (UTR) of RNA that contain a UAG trinucleotide in their core. We systematically analyzed the properties of Musashi binding elements (MBEs) in the 3′UTR of flaviviruses with a thermodynamic model for RNA folding. Our results indicate that MBEs in ZIKV 3′UTRs occur predominantly in unpaired, single-stranded structural context, thus corroborating experimental observations by a biophysical model of RNA structure formation. Statistical analysis and comparison with related viruses show that ZIKV MBEs are maximally accessible among mosquito-borne flaviviruses. Our study addresses the broader question of whether other emerging arboviruses can cause similar neurotropic effects through the same mechanism in the developing fetus by establishing a link between the biophysical properties of viral RNA and teratogenicity. Moreover, our thermodynamic model can explain recent experimental findings and predict the Msi1-related neurotropic potential of other viruses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-43390-5"&gt;Musashi Binding Elements in Zika and Related Flavivirus 3’UTRs: A Comparative Study in Silico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Adriano de Bernardi Schneider, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sci. Rep.&lt;/em&gt; 9(1):6911 (2019) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-43390-5"&gt;doi:10.1038/s41598-019-43390-5&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/deBernardiSchneider-2019a.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__deBernardiSchneider-2019a.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2022/Theoretical-studies-on-RNA-recognition-by-Musashi1-RNA-binding-protein/"&gt;Theoretical studies on RNA recognition by Musashi 1 RNA–binding protein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nitchakan Darai, Panupong Mahalapbutr, Peter Wolschann, Vannajan Sanghiran Lee, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolﬁnger&lt;/span&gt;, Thanyada Rungrotmongkol&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sci. Rep.&lt;/em&gt; 12:12137 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-16252-w"&gt;doi:10.1038/s41598-022-16252-w&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Darai-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Darai-2022.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2023/blog/2023-06-09-A-Structural-Refinement-Technique-for-Protein-RNA-Complexes-Using-Combination-of-AI-based-Modeling-and-Flexible-Docking-A-Study-of-Musashi-1-Protein/"&gt;A Structural Refinement Technique for Protein-RNA Complexes Using a Combination of AI-based Modeling and Flexible Docking: A Study of Musashi-1 Protein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Nitchakan Darai, Kowit Hengphasatporn, Peter Wolschann, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Yasuteru Shigeta, Thanyada Rungrotmongkol, Ryuhei Harada&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;B. Chem. Soc. Jpn.&lt;/em&gt; 96(7):677–685 (2023) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1246/bcsj.20230092"&gt;doi:10.1246/bcsj.20230092&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Darai-2023.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="non-coding RNA"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="ViennaRNA"></category><category term="RNA-Protein interaction"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category></entry><entry><title>Comparative look at flavivirus UTRs: Similarities and surprises</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2019/Functional_RNA_Structures_in_the_three_prime_UTR_of_Flaviviruses/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-03-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2019-03-25:/blog/2019/Functional_RNA_Structures_in_the_three_prime_UTR_of_Flaviviruses/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This study highlights the crucial role of untranslated regions (UTRs) in flaviviruses and the discovery of exoribonuclease resistant RNAs (xrRNAs). These findings showcase the importance of virus bioinformatic studies in advancing our understanding of infectious diseases and their relevance to broader health goals&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this publication, we shed light on the significance of untranslated regions (UTRs) within flavivirus, a diverse group of RNA viruses responsible for pathology in human and animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the UTRs of flaviviruses lies a wealth of RNA structural elements crucial for mediating various aspects of the viral life cycle, including genome circularization, replication, and encapsidation. These elements are far from genetic filler; they are essential components that determine the virus's ability to thrive within its host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper presents findings from a comparative genomics approach that aimed to identify evolutionarily conserved RNAs within the 3' UTR of different flaviviruses. Notably, the research supports the presence of exoribonuclease resistant RNAs (xrRNAs) in tick-borne and no-known-vector flaviviruses. These xrRNAs play a pivotal role in safeguarding viral RNA from degradation, ensuring the virus's persistence within the host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the study also unravels a cascade of duplicated RNA structures within insect-specific flaviviruses, highlighting the remarkable adaptability of these viruses in evolving novel xrRNAs. This evolutionary flexibility enables them to effectively evade host immune responses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By emphasizing the relevance of virus bioinformatics studies in synthetic biology, this research contributes to broader health goals. A deeper comprehension of the molecular intricacies of viruses and their interactions with hosts sets the stage for more efficacious strategies to combat infectious diseases, offering promising avenues for synthetic biology interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Ochsenreiter-2019.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Ochsenreiter-2019.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untranslated regions (UTRs) of flaviviruses contain a large number of RNA structural elements involved in mediating the viral life cycle, including cyclisation, replication, and encapsidation. Here we report on a comparative genomics approach to characterize evolutionarily conserved RNAs in the 3'UTR of tick-borne, insect-specific and no-known-vector flaviviruses in silico. Our data support the wide distribution of previously experimentally characterized exoribonuclease resistant RNAs (xrRNAs) within tick-borne and no-known-vector flaviviruses and provide evidence for the existence of a cascade of duplicated RNA structures within insect-specific flaviviruses. On a broader scale, our findings indicate that viral 3'UTRs represent a flexible scaffold for evolution to come up with novel xrRNAs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="figures-and-data"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figures and Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="m-imagegrid m-container-inflate"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 100.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.001.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.001.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.002.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.002.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.003.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.003.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.004.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.004.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.005.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.005.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.006.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.006.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.007.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.007.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.008.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.008.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.009.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.009.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.010.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.010.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.011.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.011.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.012.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.012.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="width: 50.000%"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.013.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.013.png" /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/v11030298"&gt;Functional RNA Structures in the 3’UTR of Tick-Borne, Insect-Specific and No Known Vector Flaviviruses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Roman Ochsenreiter, Ivo L. Hofacker, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Viruses&lt;/em&gt; 11:298 (2019) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/v11030298"&gt;doi:10.3390/v11030298&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Ochsenreiter-2019.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Ochsenreiter-2019.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Functional-RNA-Structures-in-the-3UTR-of-Mosquito-Borne-Flaviviruses/"&gt;Functional RNA Structures in the 3’UTR of Mosquito-Borne Flaviviruses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Roman Ochsenreiter, Ivo L. Hofacker&lt;br /&gt;
In &lt;em&gt;Virus Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Dmitrij Frishman and Manja Marz, pp65–100. Chapman and Hall/CRC Press (2021) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1201/9781003097679-5"&gt;doi:10.1201/9781003097679-5&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2021.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Wolfinger-2021.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2021/Evolutionary-traits-of-Tick-borne-encephalitis-virus-Pervasive-non-coding-RNA-structure-conservation-and-molecular-epidemiology/"&gt;Evolutionary traits of Tick-borne encephalitis virus: Pervasive non-coding RNA structure conservation and molecular epidemiology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lena S. Kutschera, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Virus Evol.&lt;/em&gt; (8):1 veac051 (2022) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ve/veac051"&gt;doi:10.1093/ve/veac051&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Kutschera-2022.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/QuickSlide/QuickSlide__Kutschera-2022.pdf"&gt;Figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="virus bioinformatics"></category><category term="One Health"></category><category term="xrRNA"></category><category term="flavivirus"></category><category term="synthetic biology"></category></entry><entry><title>Searching for Telomerase RNAs in Saccharomycetes is TERribly difficult</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2018/TERribly-Difficult-Searching-for-Telomerase-RNAs-in-Saccharomycetes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2018-07-26:/blog/2018/TERribly-Difficult-Searching-for-Telomerase-RNAs-in-Saccharomycetes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Telomerase RNAs are intrinsically difficult to find by homology search methods, even within phylogenetically related groups. This study reports our efforts in annotating telomerase RNAs in the Saccharomycetacea subgroup of yeasts, using the ViennaRNA Package and related tools&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Waldl-2018.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Waldl-2018.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The telomerase RNA in yeasts is large, usually &amp;gt;1000 nt, and contains functional elements that have been extensively studied experimentally in several disparate species. Nevertheless, they are very difficult to detect by homology-based methods and so far have escaped annotation in the majority of the genomes of Saccharomycotina. This is a consequence of sequences that evolve rapidly at nucleotide level, are subject to large variations in size, and are highly plastic with respect to their secondary structures. Here, we report on a survey that was aimed at closing this gap in RNA annotation. Despite considerable efforts and the combination of a variety of different methods, it was only partially successful. While 27 new telomerase RNAs were identified, we had to restrict our efforts to the subgroup Saccharomycetacea because even this narrow subgroup was diverse enough to require different search models for different phylogenetic subgroups. More distant branches of the Saccharomycotina remain without annotated telomerase RNA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/genes9080372"&gt;TERribly Difficult: Searching for Telomerase RNAs in Saccharomycetes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Maria Waldl, Bernhard C. Thiel, Roman Ochsenreiter, Alexander Holzenleiter, João Victor de Araujo Oliveira, Maria Emília M.T. Walter, Michael T. Wolfinger, Peter F. Stadler&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Genes&lt;/em&gt; 9(8),372 (2018) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/genes9080372"&gt;doi: 10.3390/genes9080372&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Waldl-2018.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="non-coding RNA"></category></entry><entry><title>Co-transcriptional riboswitch modleing with ViennaRNA</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2018/Efficient-Computation-of-Cotranscriptional-RNA-Ligand-Interaction-Dynamics/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2018-07-01:/blog/2018/Efficient-Computation-of-Cotranscriptional-RNA-Ligand-Interaction-Dynamics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Riboswitches are RNA molecules that regulate gene expression by sensing metabolites, presenting an interesting target for synthetic biology applications. We present a computational approach based on ViennaRNA tools to dissect and model RNA-ligand interaction dynamics under kinetic control, enabling simulation of riboswitch folding&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the methodology lies an extension of the BARRIERS approach, partitioning the folding landscape into distinct classes of structures based on the presence or absence of ligands. By adopting an all-or-none scenario for ligand binding, we efficiently model concentration-dependent binding and unbinding events, offering a glimpse into the dynamic behavior of riboswitches under kinetic control. Through a modified version of the BARMAP pipeline, co-transcriptional folding dynamics are meticulously computed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the I-A 2’-deoxyguanosine (2’dG)-sensing riboswitch from Mesoplasma florum, which has recently been studied by NMR spectroscopy, as an example we show that our results are in good agreement with experimental data. Computational predictions yield substantial mechanistic insight, allowing us not only to understand natural riboswitches on a mechanistic level but also to perform systematic in silico screening and analysis of novel designs before expensive experimental validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This technical study advances our understanding of riboswitch folding dynamics and offers a computational tool for engineering riboswitch-based gene regulation in synthetic biology applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2018__PREPRINT.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2018__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Riboswitches form an abundant class of cis-regulatory RNA elements that mediate gene expression by binding a small metabolite. For synthetic biology applications, they are becoming cheap and accessible systems for selectively triggering transcription or translation of downstream genes. Many riboswitches are kinetically controlled, hence knowledge of their co-transcriptional mechanisms is essential. We present here an efficient implementation for analyzing co-transcriptional RNA-ligand interaction dynamics. This approach allows for the first time to model concentration-dependent metabolite binding/unbinding kinetics. We exemplify this novel approach by means of the recently studied I-A 2′-deoxyguanosine (2′dG)-sensing riboswitch from Mesoplasma florum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2018.04.036"&gt;Efficient Computation of Cotranscriptional RNA-Ligand Interaction Dynamics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Christoph Flamm, Ivo L. Hofacker&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Methods&lt;/em&gt; 143:70–76 (2018) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2018.04.036"&gt;doi: 10.1016/j.ymeth.2018.04.036&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2018__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2017/blog/2017-01-31-NMR-Structural-Profiling-of-Transcriptional-Intermediates-Reveals-Riboswitch-Regulation-by-Metastable-RNA-Conformations/"&gt;NMR Structural Profiling of Transcriptional Intermediates Reveals Riboswitch Regulation by Metastable RNA Conformations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Christina Helmling, Anna Wacker, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Ivo L. Hofacker, Martin Hengsbach, Boris Fürtig, Harald Schwalbe&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;J. Am. Chem. Soc.&lt;/em&gt; 139 (7):2647–56 (2017) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1021/jacs.6b10429"&gt;doi:10.1021/jacs.6b10429&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="energy landscapes"></category><category term="new method"></category><category term="RNA kinetics"></category><category term="ViennaRNA"></category><category term="synthetic biology"></category></entry><entry><title>In silico design of ligand triggered RNA switches</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2018/In-Silico-Design-of-Ligand-Triggered-RNA-Switches/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2018-07-01:/blog/2018/In-Silico-Design-of-Ligand-Triggered-RNA-Switches/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the world of synthetic biology, the design of RNA switches holds immense promise for various applications, ranging from diagnostics to therapeutics. This paper presents a comprehensive workflow for designing RNA switches that can dynamically alter their structural conformations in response to specific ligands&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The research paper outlines a step-by-step RNA design process, shedding light on each crucial stage with intricate detail. From selecting a well-characterized RNA aptamer, such as the theophylline aptamer, to delineating the structural features essential for ligand binding, every aspect of the design process is elucidated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce a novel, probability-based objective function which allows researchers to quantitatively assess the performance of their designed RNA switches, making it easier to identify the most effective candidates for their specific application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on these advancements, we establish key criteria to ensure robust analysis of RNA switch behavior. This focus on rigorous methodology strengthens the foundation for reliable results in the design process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we present a method to visualize the kinetic properties of RNA switch sequences. This visualization tool provides valuable insights into the speed of structural changes within the switch, enabling researchers to efficiently rank and filter designed sequences and pinpoint the optimal candidates for further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Findeiss-2018__PREPRINT.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Findeiss-2018__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contribution sketches a work flow to design an RNA switch that is able to adapt two structural conformations in a ligand-dependent way. A well characterized RNA aptamer, i.e., knowing its Kd and adaptive structural features, is an essential ingredient of the described design process. We exemplify the principles using the well-known theophylline aptamer throughout this work. The aptamer in its ligand-binding competent structure represents one structural conformation of the switch while an alternative fold that disrupts the binding-competent structure forms the other conformation. To keep it simple we do not incorporate any regulatory mechanism to control transcription or translation. We elucidate a commonly used design process by explicitly dissecting and explaining the necessary steps in detail. We developed a novel objective function which specifies the mechanistics of this simple, ligand-triggered riboswitch and describe an extensive in silico analysis pipeline to evaluate important kinetic properties of the designed sequences. This protocol and the developed software can be easily extended or adapted to fit novel design scenarios and thus can serve as a template for future needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2018.04.003"&gt;In silico design of ligand triggered RNA switches&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sven Findeiß, Stefan Hammer, Michael T. Wolfinger, Felix Kühnl, Christoph Flamm, Ivo L.Hofacker&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Methods&lt;/em&gt; 143:90-101 (2018) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2018.04.003"&gt;doi: 10.1016/j.ymeth.2018.04.003&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Findeiss-2018__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="energy landscapes"></category><category term="new method"></category><category term="RNA kinetics"></category><category term="RNA design"></category><category term="ViennaRNA"></category><category term="synthetic biology"></category></entry><entry><title>Co-transcriptional folding as a key factor in riboswitch function</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2017/blog/2017-01-31-NMR-Structural-Profiling-of-Transcriptional-Intermediates-Reveals-Riboswitch-Regulation-by-Metastable-RNA-Conformations/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2017-01-31:/blog/2017/blog/2017-01-31-NMR-Structural-Profiling-of-Transcriptional-Intermediates-Reveals-Riboswitch-Regulation-by-Metastable-RNA-Conformations/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the realm of gene regulation, understanding the precise mechanisms by which RNA molecules fold and function during transcription is crucial. This study delves into this intricate process, focusing on the type I-A 2′-deoxyguanosine (2'dG)-sensing riboswitch from Mesoplasma florum. By employing NMR spectroscopy and computational modeling, we have uncovered critical insights into how co-transcriptional folding influences ligand binding and conformational switching in these regulatory RNAs.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Riboswitches are small, metabolite-sensing RNA molecules that regulate gene expression by undergoing structural changes upon binding to specific ligands. These conformational switches can either terminate or promote transcription, depending on the presence of the ligand. Despite extensive studies on riboswitches, the relationship between the length of the mRNA transcript, ligand binding, and the subsequent allosteric conformational changes has remained elusive—until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="investigating-co-transcriptional-folding"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Investigating co-transcriptional folding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study focuses on the I-A type 2'dG-sensing riboswitch, exploring how it folds and functions during transcription. By mapping changes in the conformational space of transcription intermediates at single-nucleotide resolution, we provide a detailed picture of the folding process. This meticulous approach reveals a fine-tuning mechanism where ligand binding and sequence-dependent alterations of the RNA structure are closely linked to the transcript length.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="key-findings"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using NMR spectroscopy, we analyzed transcription intermediates with single-nucleotide precision, offering unprecedented insights into the folding process of the riboswitch. The study highlights the importance of metastable states—temporary conformations that the RNA adopts during transcription. These states are crucial for the proper functioning of the riboswitch, ensuring that the RNA can efficiently switch structures in response to ligand binding. The findings underscore that RNA folding is highly sequence-dependent, with specific sequences promoting or hindering the formation of certain structures. This dependency plays a critical role in the riboswitch's ability to regulate gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="implications-for-synthetic-biology-and-healthcare"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Implications for synthetic biology and healthcare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the co-transcriptional folding of riboswitches opens up new avenues for the rational design of inducible molecular devices. These devices could be tailored for various applications in synthetic biology and healthcare, such as creating new biosensors or developing targeted gene regulation therapies. The knowledge gained from this study provides a framework for designing RNA molecules with precise regulatory functions, paving the way for innovative biotechnological solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gene repression induced by the formation of transcriptional terminators represents a prime example for the coupling of RNA synthesis, folding, and regulation. In this context, mapping the changes in available conformational space of transcription intermediates during RNA synthesis is important to understand riboswitch function. A majority of riboswitches, an important class of small metabolite-sensing regulatory RNAs, act as transcriptional regulators, but the dependence of ligand binding and the subsequent allosteric conformational switch on mRNA transcript length has not yet been investigated. We show a strict fine-tuning of binding and sequence-dependent alterations of conformational space by structural analysis of all relevant transcription intermediates at single-nucleotide resolution for the I-A type 2′dG-sensing riboswitch from Mesoplasma f lorum by NMR spectroscopy. Our results provide a general framework to dissect the coupling of synthesis and folding essential for riboswitch function, revealing the importance of metastable states for RNA-based gene regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Citation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1021/jacs.6b10429"&gt;NMR Structural Profiling of Transcriptional Intermediates Reveals Riboswitch Regulation by Metastable RNA Conformations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Christina Helmling, Anna Wacker, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Ivo L. Hofacker, Martin Hengsbach, Boris Fürtig, Harald Schwalbe&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;J. Am. Chem. Soc.&lt;/em&gt; 139 (7):2647–56 (2017) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1021/jacs.6b10429"&gt;doi:10.1021/jacs.6b10429&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;See also&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2018/Efficient-Computation-of-Cotranscriptional-RNA-Ligand-Interaction-Dynamics/"&gt;Efficient Computation of Cotranscriptional RNA-Ligand Interaction Dynamics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Christoph Flamm, Ivo L. Hofacker&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Methods&lt;/em&gt; 143:70–76 (2018) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2018.04.036"&gt;doi:10.1016/j.ymeth.2018.04.036&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2018__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="bacteria"></category><category term="energy landscapes"></category><category term="synthetic biology"></category></entry><entry><title>RNA structural insights through prediction and probing</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2016/Predicting-RNA-Structures-from-Sequence-and-Probing-Data/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2016-07-01:/blog/2016/Predicting-RNA-Structures-from-Sequence-and-Probing-Data/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This review explores methods for predicting RNA secondary structures by integrating reactivity information from experimental probing data. It highlights the limitations of traditional RNA structure prediction, which typically relies solely on thermodynamic models based on sequences&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We discuss how experimental techniques for chemical and enzymatic structure probing like SHAPE or PARS can provide valuable insights into RNA structure, allowing for more accurate predictions when combined with thermodynamics-only algorithms. By incorporating probing data as soft constraints or pseudo-energies in folding algorithms, we can enhance the accuracy of RNA structure models. The paper also addresses the challenges of merging these approaches and outlines future directions for improving RNA structure determination through the integration of experimental and computational methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Lorenz-2016.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Lorenz-2016.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RNA secondary structures have proven essential for understanding the regulatory functions performed by RNA such as microRNAs, bacterial small RNAs, or riboswitches. This success is in part due to the availability of efficient computational methods for predicting RNA secondary structures. Recent advances focus on ealing with the inherent uncertainty of prediction by considering the ensemble of possible structures rather than the single most stable one. Moreover, the advent of high-throughput structural probinghas spurred the development of computational methods that incorporate such experimental data as auxiliary information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2016.04.004"&gt;Predicting RNA Structures from Sequence and Probing Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ronny Lorenz, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Andrea Tanzer, Ivo L. Hofacker&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Methods&lt;/em&gt; 103:86–98 (2016) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2016.04.004"&gt;doi:10.1016/j.ymeth.2016.04.004&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Lorenz-2016.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2015/SHAPE-directed-RNA-folding/"&gt;SHAPE Directed RNA Folding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ronny Lorenz, Dominik Luntzer, Ivo L. Hofacker, Peter F. Stadler, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 32: 145–47 (2016) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btv523"&gt;doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv523&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Lorenz-2016a.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="ViennaRNA"></category><category term="RNA design"></category><category term="RNA kinetics"></category><category term="SHAPE"></category></entry><entry><title>SHAPE directed RNA folding with the ViennaRNA Package</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2015/SHAPE-directed-RNA-folding/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2015-09-02:/blog/2015/SHAPE-directed-RNA-folding/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The ViennaRNA Package 2.0 brings powerful dynamic programming algorithms to researchers studying nucleic acid folding. In this post, we explore three SHAPE-guided methods—Deigan, Zarringhalam, and Washietl—that have been integrated into our toolkit to improve predictions of base pair interactions and minimum free energy (MFE) structures for RNA molecules. By combining chemical probing data with in silico modeling, these approaches help capture real-world folding behaviors and enhance the accuracy of computational RNA structure predictions&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;section id="bridging-experiment-with-computation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bridging Experiment with Computation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern experiments generate SHAPE reactivity profiles through selective 2’-hydroxyl acylation analyzed by primer extension, a method that reveals nucleotide flexibility in vitro or in vivo. To translate these reactivities into structural guidance, the Deigan, Zarringhalam, and Washietl methods each adjust the energy parameters used in traditional dynamic programming: Deigan’s model applies pseudo-energies directly to loops, Zarringhalam’s method uses reactivity-specific weights, and Washietl’s approach infers perturbation of the energy parameters to optimally fit the SHAPE signal. Together, these innovations allow the prediction of both the minimum free energy (MFE) structure and the ensemble of probable folds with improved sensitivity to experimental data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="performance-and-benchmarking"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Performance and Benchmarking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To validate these implementations, we benchmarked against a curated set of RNAs with known reference structures, analyzing metrics like sensitivity and positive predictive value for predicted base pairs. The comparisons covered both the MFE structure and the full partition function ensemble, demonstrating that SHAPE-guided predictions outperform purely thermodynamic models, especially for challenging motifs. Detailed supplementary data outline our benchmark strategies, energy parameter settings, and the impact on diverse RNA molecules, confirming the value of integrating experimental evidence into computational pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="getting-started-command-line-and-source-code"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting Started: Command Line and Source Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users can install binary packages for several Linux distributions or build from source code available on our repository. The command line interface supports  commands for folding, partition function calculation, and SHAPE-guided modes, with options to specify and adjust energy parameters directly. Whether you’re scripting large-scale screens or running individual analyses, our tools and comprehensive documentation provide everything needed to apply dynamic programming algorithms to your nucleic acid research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a deep dive, don’t miss the &lt;a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2015/09/23/bioinformatics.btv523/suppl/DC1"&gt;Supplementary Data&lt;/a&gt;, which includes extensive background on each method, parameter details, and full benchmark results for our SHAPE-integrated algorithms. Dive into the code, explore the options, and see how experimental data can guide your next discovery in RNA structure prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Lorenz-2016a.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Lorenz-2016a.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chemical mapping experiments allow for nucleotide resolution
assessment of RNA structure. We demonstrate that different strategies of
integrating probing data with thermodynamics-based RNA secondary
structure prediction algorithms can be implemented by means of soft
constraints. This amounts to incorporating suitable pseudo-energies into
the standard energy model for RNA secondary structures. As a showcase
application for this new feature of the ViennaRNA Package we compare
three distinct, previously published strategies to utilize SHAPE
reactivities for structure prediction. The new tool is benchmarked on a
set of RNAs with known reference structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The capability for SHAPE directed RNA
folding is part of the upcoming release of the ViennaRNA Package 2.2, for
which a preliminary release is already freely available at
&lt;a class="m-link-wrap" href="http://www.tbi.univie.ac.at/RNA"&gt;http://www.tbi.univie.ac.at/RNA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Citation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2015/09/23/bioinformatics.btv523.abstract"&gt;SHAPE directed RNA folding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ronny Lorenz, Dominik Luntzer, Ivo L. Hofacker, Peter F. Stadler, Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 32: 145–47 (2016) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btv523"&gt;doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btv523&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Lorenz-2016a.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;See also&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2016/Predicting-RNA-Structures-from-Sequence-and-Probing-Data/"&gt;Predicting RNA Structures from Sequence and Probing Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ronny Lorenz, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Andrea Tanzer, Ivo L. Hofacker&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Methods&lt;/em&gt; 103:86–98 (2016) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymeth.2016.04.004"&gt;doi:10.1016/j.ymeth.2016.04.004&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Lorenz-2016.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="ViennaRNA"></category><category term="SHAPE"></category><category term="new method"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>mRNA degradation occurs on ribosome complexes in Drosophila cells</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2015/general-and-miRNA-mediated-mrna-degradation-occurs-on-ribosome-complexes-in-drosophila-cells/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2015-08-12:/blog/2015/general-and-miRNA-mediated-mrna-degradation-occurs-on-ribosome-complexes-in-drosophila-cells/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this study we show that mRNA degradation occurs on ribosome complexes in Drosophila cells&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;mRNA degradation and translation are two processes crucial for
posttranscriptional gene regulation. While the strong interconnection of
mRNA degradation and translation has been noted for many years, it has led
to the hypothesis that mRNAs could be degraded on the ribosome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present study we provide evidence that the ribosome is a universal site not only for general 5' to 3' mRNA degradation in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; but also for the miRNA-mediated mRNA degradation pathway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Antic-2015.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Antic-2015.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The translation and degradation of mRNAs are two key steps in gene
expression that are highly regulated and targeted by many factors,
including microRNAs (miRNAs). While it is well established that translation
and mRNA degradation are tightly coupled, it is still not entirely clear
where in the cell mRNA degradation takes place. In this study, we
investigated the possibility of mRNA degradation on the ribosome in
Drosophila cells. Using polysome profiles and ribosome affinity
purification, we could demonstrate the copurification of various
deadenylation and decapping factors with ribosome complexes. Also, AGO1 and
GW182, two key factors in the miRNA-mediated mRNA degradation pathway, were
associated with ribosome complexes. Their copurification was dependent on
intact mRNAs, suggesting the association of these factors with the mRNA
rather than the ribosome itself. Furthermore, we isolated decapped mRNA
degradation intermediates from ribosome complexes and performed
high-throughput sequencing analysis. Interestingly, 93% of the decapped
mRNA fragments (approximately 12,000) could be detected at the same
relative abundance on ribosome complexes and in cell lysates. In summary,
our findings strongly indicate the association of the majority of bulk
mRNAs as well as mRNAs targeted by miRNAs with the ribosome during their
degradation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="http://mcb.asm.org/content/35/13/2309"&gt;General and miRNA-mediated mRNA degradation occurs on ribosome complexes in Drosophila cells&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sanja Antic, Michael T. Wolfinger, Anna Skucha, Stefanie Hosiner and Silke Dorner&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mol. Cell. Biol.&lt;/em&gt; 35(13), 2309-2320 (2015) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1128/MCB.01346-14"&gt;doi:10.1128/MCB.01346-14&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Antic-2015.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="NGS"></category></entry><entry><title>Building efficient NGS analysis pipelines with ViennaNGS</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2015/ViennaNGS-a-toolbox-for-building-efficient-next-generation-sequencing-analysis-pipelines/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2015-03-02:/blog/2015/ViennaNGS-a-toolbox-for-building-efficient-next-generation-sequencing-analysis-pipelines/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;ViennaNGS is a workflow system for building efficient NGS data analysis pipelines, integrating high-level routines and wrapper functions for common NGS processing tasks&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;ViennaNGS&lt;/em&gt; is not an established pipeline per
se, it provides tools and functionality for the development of custom NGS
pipelines in Perl. &lt;em&gt;ViennaNGS&lt;/em&gt; comes with a set of utility scripts that serve as
reference implementation for most library functions and can readily be applied
for specific tasks or integrated as-is into custom pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ViennaNGS&lt;/em&gt; covers a broad range of NGS data processing tasks, including
functionality for extracting and converting features from common NGS file
formats, computation and evaluation of read mapping statistics, quantification
and normalization of read count data, identification and characterization of
splice junctions from RNA-seq data, parsing and condensing sequence motif data,
automated construction of Assembly and Track Hubs for the UCSC genome browser
and wrapper routines for a set of commonly used NGS command line tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ViennaNGS suite is available through &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://github.com/mtw/Bio-ViennaNGS"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://metacpan.org/dist/Bio-ViennaNGS"&gt;CPAN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2015.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2015.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent achievements in next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies lead to a high demand for reuseable software components to easily compile customized analysis workflows for big genomics data. We present ViennaNGS, an integrated collection of Perl modules focused on building efficient pipelines for NGS data processing. It comes with functionality for extracting and converting features from common NGS file formats, computation and evaluation of read mapping statistics, as well as normalization of RNA abundance. Moreover, ViennaNGS provides software components for identification and characterization of splice junctions from RNA-seq data, parsing and condensing sequence motif data, automated construction of Assembly and Track Hubs for the UCSC genome browser, as well as wrapper routines for a set of commonly used NGS command line tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.6157.2"&gt;ViennaNGS: A toolbox for building efficient next-generation sequencing analysis pipelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Michael T. Wolfinger, Jörg Fallmann, Florian Eggenhofer, Fabian Amman&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;F1000Research&lt;/em&gt; 4:50 (2015) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.6157.2"&gt;doi: 10.12688/f1000research.6157.2&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2015.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="NGS"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>How to efficiently explore the lower portion of RNA energy landscapes</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2014/Memory-efficient-RNA-energy-landscape-exploration/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2014-06-12:/blog/2014/Memory-efficient-RNA-energy-landscape-exploration/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Discrete energy landscapes provide a valuable means for analyzing non-equilibrium properties of biopolymers. In this study we propose a memory-efficient approach for local flooding of the lower portion of an RNA folding landscape&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The dynamic process of RNA folding can be modeled as a continuous-time Markov process, focusing on local minima, their associated basins of attraction, and the saddle points that connect them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To construct an energy landscape, a connected set of RNA structures, commonly referred to as the state space, is required, along with a neighborhood relation between these states and an assigned energy or fitness value. Although obtaining the complete suboptimal folding for RNA sequences longer than 100 nucleotides is computationally impractical, various strategies have been developed to explore the lower-energy portion of the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this work, we introduce a local variant of our previous global flooding approach to energy landscapes. This localized flooding technique significantly reduces memory usage, allowing for the analysis of energy landscapes for longer RNA sequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mann-2014.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mann-2014.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation:&lt;/strong&gt; Energy landscapes provide a valuable means for studying the
folding dynamics of short RNA molecules in detail by modeling all
possible structures and their transitions. Higher abstraction levels
based on a macro-state decomposition of the landscape enable the study of
larger systems; however, they are still restricted by huge memory
requirements of exact approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt; We present a highly parallelizable local enumeration scheme that
enables the computation of exact macro-state transition models with
highly reduced memory requirements. The approach is evaluated on RNA
secondary structure landscapes using a gradient basin definition for
macro-states. Furthermore, we demonstrate the need for exact transition
models by comparing two barrier-based approaches, and perform a detailed
investigation of gradient basins in RNA energy landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Availability and implementation:&lt;/strong&gt; Source code is part of the &lt;a href="https://www.bioinf.uni-freiburg.de/subpage/software/libraries.html#lib_ell"&gt;C++ Energy Landscape Library&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/30/18/2584"&gt;Memory-efficient RNA energy landscape exploration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Martin Mann, Marcel Kucharík, Christoph Flamm, Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 30(18):2584-2591 (2014) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btu337"&gt;doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btu337&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mann-2014.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2006/Exploring-the-Lower-Part-of-Discrete-Polymer-Model-Energy-Landscapes/"&gt;Exploring the Lower Part of Discrete Polymer Model Energy Landscapes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Sebastian Will, Ivo L. Hofacker, Rolf Backofen, Peter F. Stadler&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Europhys. Lett.&lt;/em&gt; 74(4): 726–32 (2006) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1209/epl/i2005-10577-0"&gt;doi:10.1209/epl/i2005-10577-0&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2006__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2002/Barrier-Trees-of-Degenerate-Landscapes/"&gt;Barrier Trees of Degenerate Landscapes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Christoph Flamm, Ivo L. Hofacker, Peter F. Stadler, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Z. Phys. Chem.&lt;/em&gt; 216: 155–73 (2002) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1524/zpch.2002.216.2.155"&gt;doi:10.1524/zpch.2002.216.2.155&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Flamm-2002__PRPERINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="energy landscapes"></category><category term="new method"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>How to compute normalized RNA-seq expression from multicov files</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2014/How-to-compute-normalized-RNA-seq-expression-from-multicov-files/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2014-04-15:/blog/2014/How-to-compute-normalized-RNA-seq-expression-from-multicov-files/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why you should use TPM rather than RPKM&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whenever it comes to analyzing RNA-seq experiments, there is a need for comparing expression data at a quantitative level. Consider a scenario where samples were taken from different conditions and subjected to Illumina sequencing. Whether those samples were multiplexed or sequenced on a single lane each, one generally gets a different number of raw reads from each sample, refelcting experimental and technical biases inherent in the RNA-seq protocols. Various measures for normalization of RNA-seq samples have been proposed, the most widely used being RPKM (reads per kilobase per million). While RPKM tries to account for different sequencing depth by normalizing by the number of reads sequenced in a specific sample, divided by 10^6. This very step causes a systematic bias, as has been shown here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="http://doi.org/10.1007/s12064-012-0162-3"&gt;Measurement of mRNA abundance using RNA-seq data: RPKM measure is inconsistent among samples&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Günter P. Wagner, Koryu Kin, Vincent J. Lynch&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Theory Biosci.&lt;/em&gt; 131, 281-285 (2012) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12064-012-0162-3"&gt;doi:10.1007/s12064-012-0162-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="http://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp692"&gt;RNA-Seq gene expression estimation with read mapping uncertainty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bo Li, Victor Ruotti, Ron M. Stewart, James A. Thomson, Colin N. Dewey&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 6(4), 493-500. (2009) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp692"&gt;doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btp692&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central point of these papers is to work out an alternative measure for
RNA-seq expression abundance that resembles as closely as possible the
&lt;em&gt;relative molar concentration&lt;/em&gt; (rmc) of each RNA species present in a
sample. It is easy to see that the average rmc across genes has to be a
constant that only depends on the number of genes mapped in an RNA-seq
experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example of measures that fulfills the invariant average criterion is
&lt;em&gt;Transcript per million&lt;/em&gt; (TPM), being defined as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="m-math"&gt;
&lt;svg version='1.1' xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink' width='78.922067pt' height='15.969084pt' viewBox='-.956413 -11.827084 78.922067 15.969084'&gt;
&lt;defs&gt;
&lt;path id='g21-48' d='M4.157561-2.882343C4.157561-4.672889 3.362733-5.904436 2.218531-5.904436C1.73814-5.904436 1.371296-5.755951 1.048125-5.450248C.541531-4.961124 .209625-3.956671 .209625-2.934749C.209625-1.982703 .497859-.960781 .908375-.471656C1.231547-.087344 1.677 .122281 2.183593 .122281C2.629046 .122281 3.004624-.026203 3.319062-.331906C3.825655-.812297 4.157561-1.825484 4.157561-2.882343ZM3.319062-2.864874C3.319062-1.03939 2.934749-.104812 2.183593-.104812S1.048125-1.03939 1.048125-2.85614C1.048125-4.707827 1.441171-5.677342 2.192327-5.677342C2.926015-5.677342 3.319062-4.690358 3.319062-2.864874Z'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g21-49' d='M3.441343 0V-.131016C2.751327-.13975 2.611577-.227094 2.611577-.646344V-5.886967L2.541702-5.904436L.969515-5.109608V-4.987327C1.074328-5.030999 1.170406-5.065936 1.205343-5.083405C1.362562-5.144545 1.511046-5.179483 1.59839-5.179483C1.781812-5.179483 1.860421-5.048467 1.860421-4.768967V-.812297C1.860421-.524062 1.790546-.323172 1.650796-.244562C1.519781-.165953 1.3975-.13975 1.030656-.131016V0H3.441343Z'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g21-54' d='M4.087686-1.912828C4.087686-3.030827 3.450077-3.738311 2.445624-3.738311C2.061312-3.738311 1.87789-3.677171 1.327625-3.345265C1.563453-4.664155 2.541702-5.607467 3.912999-5.834561L3.89553-5.974311C2.899812-5.886967 2.393218-5.721014 1.755609-5.275561C.812297-4.603014 .296969-3.607296 .296969-2.43689C.296969-1.677 .532797-.908375 .908375-.471656C1.240281-.087344 1.711937 .122281 2.253468 .122281C3.33653 .122281 4.087686-.707484 4.087686-1.912828ZM3.301593-1.615859C3.301593-.655078 2.960952-.122281 2.349546-.122281C1.580921-.122281 1.109265-.943312 1.109265-2.29714C1.109265-2.742593 1.17914-2.987155 1.353828-3.118171C1.53725-3.257921 1.808015-3.33653 2.113718-3.33653C2.864874-3.33653 3.301593-2.707655 3.301593-1.615859Z'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g3-61' d='M6.574598-3.930466V-4.597454H.47642V-3.930466H6.574598ZM6.574598-1.512634V-2.179622H.47642V-1.512634H6.574598Z'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g5-3' d='M4.871396-3.978108C4.871396-4.180587 4.704649-4.394976 4.49026-4.394976C4.216318-4.394976 3.239657-3.418315 2.894252-3.215836C2.894252-3.882824 3.227747-4.549812 3.227747-4.95477C3.227747-5.20489 3.060999-5.359727 2.810879-5.359727C2.572669-5.359727 2.429743-5.19298 2.429743-4.95477C2.429743-4.49026 2.715595-3.859003 2.715595-3.215836C2.334459-3.442136 1.405439-4.442618 1.155319-4.442618C.94093-4.442618 .750362-4.240139 .750362-4.02575C.750362-3.608883 2.155801-3.323031 2.620311-3.060999C2.12007-2.775147 1.19105-2.632221 .95284-2.477385C.833735-2.394011 .738451-2.286817 .738451-2.13198C.738451-1.917591 .905198-1.727023 1.119587-1.727023C1.393529-1.727023 2.35828-2.691774 2.715595-2.894252C2.715595-2.239175 2.382101-1.572186 2.382101-1.155319C2.382101-.917109 2.560758-.750362 2.798968-.750362S3.180104-.929019 3.180104-1.155319C3.180104-1.64365 2.906163-2.262996 2.906163-2.894252C3.275389-2.679863 4.216318-1.679381 4.454528-1.679381C4.668917-1.679381 4.859486-1.88186 4.859486-2.096249C4.859486-2.251085 4.752291-2.35828 4.633186-2.429743C4.323513-2.632221 3.501688-2.763237 2.989536-3.060999C3.54933-3.394494 4.311602-3.442136 4.657007-3.644614C4.788022-3.716077 4.871396-3.823272 4.871396-3.978108Z'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g8-54' d='M2.286223-.41925C1.997989 .694383 1.663899 1.303606 1.093981 1.303606C.687832 1.303606 .831949 .956414 .50441 .956414C.432352 .956414 .255481 1.054676 .255481 1.218446C.255481 1.493579 .779543 1.545985 1.028473 1.545985C1.270852 1.545985 1.696653 1.473926 2.00454 1.152938C2.384485 .75334 2.59411 .49786 2.856141-.661629L3.314696-2.823388C3.157477-2.823388 2.980606-2.803735 2.849591-2.836489C2.67272-2.856141 2.587559-2.875794 2.318977-2.875794C1.604942-2.875794 .550266-1.92593 .550266-.845051C.550266-.478207 .694383 .072059 1.244649 .072059C1.59184 .072059 1.991438-.294785 2.384485-.877805L2.286223-.41925ZM2.502399-1.434622C2.187962-.845051 1.663899-.294785 1.454274-.294785C1.231547-.294785 1.113633-.58957 1.113633-.956414C1.113633-1.650797 1.742508-2.666169 2.33863-2.666169C2.476196-2.666169 2.613762-2.626864 2.738227-2.548255C2.738227-2.548255 2.607212-1.84077 2.502399-1.434622Z'/&gt;
&lt;use id='g24-48' xlink:href='#g21-48' transform='scale(1.363636)'/&gt;
&lt;use id='g24-49' xlink:href='#g21-49' transform='scale(1.363636)'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g12-34' d='M5.721014-.75989C5.694811-.532797 5.581264-.270766 5.345436-.253297L5.118342-.235828C5.083405-.235828 5.030999-.209625 5.030999-.165953L5.01353 0L5.030999 .017469C5.43278 .008734 5.686076 0 5.930639 0C6.183936 0 6.480904 .008734 6.873951 .017469L6.89142 0L6.908889-.165953C6.917623-.209625 6.882685-.227094 6.830279-.235828L6.603186-.253297C6.393561-.270766 6.341154-.384312 6.341154-.567734C6.341154-.628875 6.349889-.690015 6.358623-.75989L6.89142-5.01353C6.917623-5.240623 7.03117-5.362905 7.284467-5.380373L7.51156-5.397842C7.555232-5.397842 7.607638-5.397842 7.616373-5.458983L7.633842-5.63367L7.616373-5.651139H6.515842L3.869327-1.205343C3.816921-1.118 3.790718-1.083062 3.773249-1.083062C3.747046-1.083062 3.738311-1.118 3.729577-1.196609L2.873609-5.642405L1.615859-5.651139L1.59839-5.63367L1.580921-5.458983C1.580921-5.424045 1.589656-5.397842 1.650796-5.397842L1.886624-5.380373C2.087515-5.362905 2.166124-5.310498 2.166124-5.188217C2.166124-5.135811 2.15739-5.083405 2.139921-5.01353L.908375-.751156C.847234-.515328 .733687-.270766 .471656-.253297L.244562-.235828C.192156-.235828 .157219-.209625 .157219-.165953L.13975 0L.157219 .017469C.410516 .008734 .69875 0 .89964 0S1.423703 .008734 1.668265 .017469L1.694468 0L1.703203-.165953C1.703203-.209625 1.677-.235828 1.633328-.235828L1.423703-.253297C1.25775-.262031 1.196609-.375578 1.196609-.524062C1.196609-.593937 1.205343-.672547 1.231547-.751156L2.332077-4.576811H2.349546L3.19678-.043672C3.214249 .017469 3.257921 .052406 3.310327 .052406C3.353999 .052406 3.397671 .026203 3.441343-.043672L6.227608-4.664155H6.245076L5.721014-.75989Z'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g12-37' d='M2.541702-5.01353C2.585374-5.266827 2.698921-5.415311 3.301593-5.415311C3.799452-5.415311 4.271108-5.258092 4.271108-4.541874C4.271108-4.410858 4.253639-4.262374 4.218702-4.087686C4.03528-3.144374 3.511218-2.760062 2.698921-2.760062C2.489296-2.760062 2.201062-2.77753 2.113718-2.803734L2.541702-5.01353ZM1.004453-.62014C.960781-.375578 .812297-.2795 .471656-.253297L.253297-.235828C.209625-.235828 .183422-.209625 .174687-.165953L.13975 0L.157219 .017469C.462922 .008734 .882172 0 1.231547 0C1.563453 0 1.982703 .008734 2.375749 .017469L2.393218 0L2.428156-.165953C2.43689-.209625 2.410687-.235828 2.375749-.235828L2.070046-.253297C1.799281-.270766 1.677-.331906 1.677-.506594C1.677-.541531 1.677-.576469 1.685734-.62014L2.061312-2.550437C2.235999-2.489296 2.384484-2.463093 2.681452-2.463093C4.209968-2.463093 4.847577-3.502483 4.987327-4.244905C5.004795-4.332249 5.01353-4.419592 5.01353-4.524405C5.01353-5.039733 4.716561-5.71228 3.423874-5.71228C3.205515-5.71228 2.663984-5.63367 2.323343-5.63367C1.991437-5.63367 1.563453-5.642405 1.25775-5.651139L1.231547-5.63367L1.196609-5.450248C1.187875-5.415311 1.205343-5.397842 1.240281-5.397842L1.563453-5.380373C1.685734-5.371639 1.869156-5.310498 1.869156-5.100873C1.869156-5.07467 1.869156-5.039733 1.860421-5.01353L1.004453-.62014Z'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g12-41' d='M2.000171-5.63367C1.773078-5.63367 1.589656-5.71228 1.380031-5.747217C1.266484-5.319233 1.161672-5.065936 .969515-4.611749C1.03939-4.568077 1.152937-4.541874 1.231547-4.541874C1.484843-5.118342 1.703203-5.29303 2.166124-5.29303H2.768796C3.109437-5.29303 3.161843-5.205686 3.118171-4.952389L2.288406-.663812C2.235999-.41925 2.104984-.296969 1.746874-.262031L1.476109-.235828C1.441171-.200891 1.423703-.061141 1.45864 .017469C1.851687 .008734 2.166124 0 2.506765 0C2.838671 0 3.231718 .008734 3.61603 .017469C3.642233-.017469 3.668436-.192156 3.642233-.235828L3.345265-.262031C3.004624-.288234 2.908546-.401781 2.960952-.663812L3.790718-4.926186C3.851858-5.223155 3.965405-5.29303 4.262374-5.29303H4.73403C5.188217-5.29303 5.319233-5.065936 5.467717-4.480733C5.555061-4.480733 5.624936-4.480733 5.729748-4.524405C5.63367-5.022264 5.607467-5.397842 5.63367-5.747217C5.345436-5.694811 5.231889-5.63367 4.917452-5.63367H2.000171Z'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g12-54' d='M3.048296-.559C2.663984 .925843 2.218531 1.73814 1.45864 1.73814C.917109 1.73814 1.109265 1.275218 .672547 1.275218C.576469 1.275218 .340641 1.3975 .340641 1.615859C.340641 1.982703 1.030656 2.052578 1.353828 2.052578C1.668265 2.052578 2.235999 1.956499 2.63778 1.528515C3.13564 .995718 3.41514 .663812 3.75578-.882172L4.393389-3.764515C4.183764-3.764515 3.956671-3.738311 3.781983-3.781983C3.546155-3.808186 3.432608-3.834389 3.083233-3.834389C2.148656-3.834389 .75989-2.57664 .75989-1.135468C.75989-.646344 .952047 .087344 1.685734 .087344C2.148656 .087344 2.681452-.393047 3.205515-1.170406L3.048296-.559ZM3.33653-1.912828C2.908546-1.126734 2.201062-.393047 1.921562-.393047C1.624593-.393047 1.45864-.786094 1.45864-1.275218C1.45864-2.201062 2.305874-3.563624 3.109437-3.563624C3.292858-3.563624 3.485015-3.502483 3.650968-3.397671C3.650968-3.397671 3.47628-2.454359 3.33653-1.912828Z'/&gt;
&lt;path id='g12-67' d='M1.624593-3.747046L1.161672-3.720843C.995718-3.712108 .934578-3.642233 .917109-3.572358C.908375-3.546155 .882172-3.441343 .882172-3.423874S.908375-3.406405 .934578-3.406405H1.545984L1.013187-1.030656C.952047-.751156 .890906-.48039 .890906-.314437C.890906 0 1.048125 .087344 1.31889 .087344C1.711937 .087344 2.288406-.270766 2.585374-.812297C2.559171-.925843 2.498031-.97825 2.393218-.97825C1.991437-.524062 1.834218-.436719 1.694468-.436719C1.668265-.436719 1.580921-.454187 1.580921-.559C1.580921-.637609 1.607125-.812297 1.677-1.109265L2.192327-3.406405H3.048296C3.153108-3.450077 3.231718-3.677171 3.13564-3.747046H2.270937L2.358281-4.140093C2.393218-4.306046 2.471827-4.559342 2.471827-4.664155C2.471827-4.812639 2.401952-4.899983 2.122453-4.899983C1.808015-4.899983 1.825484-4.506936 1.73814-4.183764L1.624593-3.747046Z'/&gt;
&lt;use id='g16-34' xlink:href='#g12-34' transform='scale(1.363636)'/&gt;
&lt;use id='g16-37' xlink:href='#g12-37' transform='scale(1.363636)'/&gt;
&lt;use id='g16-41' xlink:href='#g12-41' transform='scale(1.363636)'/&gt;
&lt;/defs&gt;
&lt;g id='page1'&gt;
&lt;use x='-.956413' y='0' xlink:href='#g16-41'/&gt;
&lt;use x='7.041587' y='0' xlink:href='#g16-37'/&gt;
&lt;use x='14.017415' y='0' xlink:href='#g16-34'/&gt;
&lt;use x='23.250789' y='1.793263' xlink:href='#g12-54'/&gt;
&lt;use x='31.619871' y='0' xlink:href='#g3-61'/&gt;
&lt;use x='42.906825' y='-6.927103' xlink:href='#g12-67'/&gt;
&lt;use x='45.576414' y='-5.612042' xlink:href='#g8-54'/&gt;
&lt;rect x='43.213674' y='-3.407221' height='.669486' width='6.289905'/&gt;
&lt;use x='43.0096' y='4.124532' xlink:href='#g12-41'/&gt;
&lt;use x='53.355755' y='0' xlink:href='#g5-3'/&gt;
&lt;use x='61.6433' y='0' xlink:href='#g24-49'/&gt;
&lt;use x='67.620884' y='0' xlink:href='#g24-48'/&gt;
&lt;use x='73.598468' y='-4.339714' xlink:href='#g21-54'/&gt;
&lt;/g&gt;
&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;where t_g is a proxy for the number of transcripts that can be explained by
a certain number of mapped reads and T is the sum of all t_g over all
genes. If one is interested in mRNA abundance, the  average TPM - and thus
the average rmc is inversely proportional to the number of features
present in a reference annotation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practically, TPM values for individual genes can be computed from read
count tables, ie. tables that give the number of reads overlapping a
specific gene. Typical programs for obtaining read count tables are
&lt;a href="http://htseq.readthedocs.io/"&gt;htseq-count&lt;/a&gt;
or
&lt;a href="http://bedtools.readthedocs.org/en/latest/content/tools/multicov.html"&gt;multiBamCov&lt;/a&gt;
(see &lt;a href="http://bedtools.readthedocs.org/en/latest/index.html"&gt;bedtools&lt;/a&gt; multicov).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently implemented
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mtw/ViennaNGS/blob/master/scripts/normalize_multicov.pl"&gt;normalize_multicov.pl&lt;/a&gt;,
a tool for computing normalized RNA-seq expression in terms of TPM from
multicov files. It is part of the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mtw/ViennaNGS"&gt;ViennaNGS&lt;/a&gt; Perl Modules for NGS analysis
and very easy to use: Just provide it the output of a bedtols multicov run
on your data as well as the read length used for sequencing your samples
and get back a normalized multicov file of your samples in terms of
TPM. That's all ...&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="HOWTO"></category><category term="NGS"></category></entry><entry><title>Bacterial transcription start site annotation from dRNA-seq data</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2014/TSSAR-tss-annotation-regime-for-drna-seq-data/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2014-04-13:/blog/2014/TSSAR-tss-annotation-regime-for-drna-seq-data/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A RESTful web service and standalone application for automated de-novo annotation of bacterial transcription start sites from dRNA-seq data&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In silico&lt;/em&gt; identification of bacterial transcription start sites (TSS) has
been a major challenge for the last years. To address this issue, we have
developped &lt;a href="http://rna.tbi.univie.ac.at/TSSAR"&gt;TSSAR&lt;/a&gt;, a statistical method
for analyzing dRNA-seq data, together with colleagues from the
Bioinformatics department at the University of Leipzig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Amman-2014.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Amman-2014.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt; Differential RNA sequencing dRNA-seq is a high-throughput screening
technique designed to examine the architecture of bacterial operons in
general and the precise position of transcription start sites (TSS) in
particular. Hitherto, dRNA-seq data were analyzed by visualizing the
sequencing reads mapped to the reference genome and manually annotating
reliable positions. This is very labor intensive and, due to the
subjectivity, biased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results:&lt;/strong&gt; Here, we present &lt;strong&gt;TSSAR&lt;/strong&gt;, a tool for automated de-novo TSS annotation
from dRNA-seq data that respects the statistics of dRNA-seq
libraries. &lt;strong&gt;TSSAR&lt;/strong&gt; uses the premise that the number of sequencing reads
starting at a certain genomic position within a transcriptional active
region follows a Poisson distribution with a parameter that depends on the
local strength of expression. The differences of two dRNA-seq library
counts thus follow a Skellam distribution. This provides a statistical
basis to identify significantly enriched primary transcripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We assessed the performance by analyzing a publicly available dRNA-seq
data set using &lt;strong&gt;TSSAR&lt;/strong&gt; and two simple approaches that utilize
user-defined score cutoffs. We evaluated the power of reproducing the
manual TSS annotation. Furthermore, the same data set was used to
reproduce 74 experimentally validated TSS in &lt;em&gt;H. pylori&lt;/em&gt; from reliable
techniques such as RACE or primer extension. Both analyses showed that
&lt;strong&gt;TSSAR&lt;/strong&gt; outperforms the static cutoff-dependent approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt; Having an automated and efficient tool for analyzing dRNA-seq data
facilitates the use of the dRNA-seq technique and promotes its
application to more sophisticated analysis. For instance, monitoring the
plasticity and dynamics of the transcriptomal architecture triggered by
different stimuli and growth conditions becomes possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main asset of a novel tool for dRNA-seq analysis that reaches out to
a broad user community is usability. As such, we provide &lt;strong&gt;TSSAR&lt;/strong&gt; both as
intuitive RESTful Web service &lt;a class="m-link-wrap" href="http://rna.tbi.univie.ac.at/TSSAR"&gt;http://rna.tbi.univie.ac.at/TSSAR&lt;/a&gt; together
with a set of post-processing and analysis tools, as well as a
stand-alone version for use in high-throughput dRNA-seq data analysis
pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2105/15/89"&gt;TSSAR: TSS annotation regime for dRNA-seq data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Fabian Amman, Michael T. Wolfinger, Ronny Lorenz, Ivo L. Hofacker, Peter F. Stadler, Sven Findeiß&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;BMC Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 15:89 (2014) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-15-89"&gt;doi: 10.1186/1471-2105-15-89&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Amman-2014.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="NGS"></category><category term="bacteria"></category><category term="new method"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>Exploring the Lower Part of Discrete Polymer Model Energy Landscapes</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2006/Exploring-the-Lower-Part-of-Discrete-Polymer-Model-Energy-Landscapes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2006-04-14T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2006-04-14:/blog/2006/Exploring-the-Lower-Part-of-Discrete-Polymer-Model-Energy-Landscapes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we introduce a novel approach to exploring the energy landscapes of discrete polymer models, with a particular emphasis on the lower-energy regions that play a critical role in understanding biopolymer folding behavior&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We propose a generic, problem-agnostic algorithm designed for global flooding of the low-energy portions of these landscapes. To demonstrate the effectiveness and versatility of our method, we apply it to lattice proteins in both two and three dimensions as an example application. This innovative algorithm allows to efficiently investigate the complex energy landscapes of discrete systems, providing valuable insights into the topological traits that impact biopolymer folding dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2006__PREPRINT.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2006__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present a generic, problem-independent algorithm for exploration of the low-energy portion of the energy landscape of discrete systems and apply it to the energy landscape of lattice proteins. Starting from a set of optimal and near-optimal conformations derived from a constraint-based search technique, we are able to selectively investigate the lower part of lattice protein energy landscapes in two and three dimensions. This novel approach allows, in contrast to exhaustive enumeration, for an efficient calculation of optimal and near-optimal structures below a given energy threshold and is only limited by the available amount of memory. A straightforward application of the algorithm is the calculation of barrier trees (representing the energy landscape), which then allows dynamics studies based on landscape theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1209/epl/i2005-10577-0"&gt;Exploring the Lower Part of Discrete Polymer Model Energy Landscapes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Sebastian Will, Ivo L. Hofacker, Rolf Backofen, Peter F. Stadler&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Europhys. Lett.&lt;/em&gt; 74(4): 726–32 (2006) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1209/epl/i2005-10577-0"&gt;doi:10.1209/epl/i2005-10577-0&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2006__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2014/Memory-efficient-RNA-energy-landscape-exploration/"&gt;Memory Efficient RNA Energy Landscape Exploration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Martin Mann, Marcel Kucharík, Christoph Flamm, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 30: 2584–91 (2014) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btu337"&gt;doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btu337&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mann-2014.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;BarMap: RNA Folding on Dynamic Energy Landscapes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ivo L. Hofacker, Christoph Flamm, Michael Heine, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Gerik Scheuermann, Peter F. Stadler&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;RNA&lt;/em&gt; 16:1308–16 (2010) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1261/rna.2093310"&gt;doi:10.1261/rna.2093310&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Hofacker-2010.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Efficient Computation of RNA Folding Dynamics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, W. Andreas Svrcek-Seiler, Christoph Flamm, Ivo L. Hofacker, Peter F. Stadler&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;J. Phys. A: Math. Gen.&lt;/em&gt; 37(17): 4731–41 (2004) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1088/0305-4470/37/17/005"&gt;doi:10.1088/0305-4470/37/17/005&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2004.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2002/Barrier-Trees-of-Degenerate-Landscapes/"&gt;Barrier Trees of Degenerate Landscapes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Christoph Flamm, Ivo L. Hofacker, Peter F. Stadler, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Z. Phys. Chem.&lt;/em&gt; 216: 155–73 (2002) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1524/zpch.2002.216.2.155"&gt;doi:10.1524/zpch.2002.216.2.155&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Flamm-2002__PRPERINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="energy landscapes"></category><category term="new method"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry><entry><title>Barrier Trees of Degenerate Landscapes</title><link href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2002/Barrier-Trees-of-Degenerate-Landscapes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2002-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>mtw</name></author><id>tag:michaelwolfinger.com,2002-07-01:/blog/2002/Barrier-Trees-of-Degenerate-Landscapes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This method paper introduces the concept of barrier trees, a convenient approach to describe the landscape of an optimization function. Barrier trees represent the toplogical characteristics of an energy landscape, such as a unique partitioning into local minima as leaves of the tree and saddle points as internal nodes connecting different minima.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The decomposition of non-degenerate landscapes into basins surrounding local minima connected by saddle points is straightforward. This paper extends the concept to degenerate landscapes, where the situation is more complex. We present the program 'barriers' that efficiently computes barrier trees for degenerate landscapes. This approach involves discretizing the search space, and constructing the barrier tree from i) a a set of states, ii) a neighborhood relation between states, and iii) an energy of fitness function assigned to each state. The resulting topology is visualized as a tree, and made accessible for further processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Flamm-2002__PRPERINT.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="1050px"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser does not support PDFs.
   &lt;a href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Flamm-2002__PRPERINT.pdf"&gt;Download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/object&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;aside class="m-frame"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heights of energy barriers separating two (macro-)states are useful for estimating transition frequencies. In non-degenerate landscapes the decomposition of a landscape into basins surrounding local minima connected by saddle points is straightforward and yields a useful definition of macro-states. In this work we develop a rigorous concept of barrier trees for degenerate landscapes. We present a program that efficiently computes such barrier trees, and apply it to two well known examples of landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="citation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://doi.org/10.1524/zpch.2002.216.2.155"&gt;Barrier Trees of Degenerate Landscapes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Christoph Flamm, Ivo L. Hofacker, Peter F. Stadler, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Z. Phys. Chem.&lt;/em&gt; 216: 155–73 (2002) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1524/zpch.2002.216.2.155"&gt;doi:10.1524/zpch.2002.216.2.155&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Flamm-2002__PRPERINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2014/Memory-efficient-RNA-energy-landscape-exploration/"&gt;Memory Efficient RNA Energy Landscape Exploration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Martin Mann, Marcel Kucharík, Christoph Flamm, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; 30: 2584–91 (2014) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btu337"&gt;doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btu337&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Mann-2014.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;BarMap: RNA Folding on Dynamic Energy Landscapes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ivo L. Hofacker, Christoph Flamm, Michael Heine, &lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Gerik Scheuermann, Peter F. Stadler&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;RNA&lt;/em&gt; 16:1308–16 (2010) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1261/rna.2093310"&gt;doi:10.1261/rna.2093310&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Hofacker-2010.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a class="m-flat m-text m-strong" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/blog/2006/Exploring-the-Lower-Part-of-Discrete-Polymer-Model-Energy-Landscapes/"&gt;Exploring the Lower Part of Discrete Polymer Model Energy Landscapes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, Sebastian Will, Ivo L. Hofacker, Rolf Backofen, Peter F. Stadler&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Europhys. Lett.&lt;/em&gt; 74(4): 726–32 (2006) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1209/epl/i2005-10577-0"&gt;doi:10.1209/epl/i2005-10577-0&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2006__PREPRINT.pdf"&gt;Preprint PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Efficient Computation of RNA Folding Dynamics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="m-text m-ul"&gt;Michael T. Wolfinger&lt;/span&gt;, W. Andreas Svrcek-Seiler, Christoph Flamm, Ivo L. Hofacker, Peter F. Stadler&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;J. Phys. A: Math. Gen.&lt;/em&gt; 37(17): 4731–41 (2004) | &lt;a class="doi" href="https://doi.org/10.1088/0305-4470/37/17/005"&gt;doi:10.1088/0305-4470/37/17/005&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a class="m-flat m-text" href="https://michaelwolfinger.com/files/papers/Wolfinger-2004.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="publications"></category><category term="energy landscapes"></category><category term="new method"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry></feed>